Good morning. Welcome back. So, any
questions from yesterday?
Uh any questions or comments?
Uh yes.
Uh hey. Uh I had this weird dream last
night.
>> Okay. Uh so so in the dream like we were
discussing you you were like doing
compare and contrast uh between Final
Fantasy 7 and the other like stories and
all all of a sudden I was I was set on a
journey to look for a answer right and
and like like intuitively
uh sorry like I know I I I I feel like
there's a tree and
and I I I knew like the tree probably
has the answer that I'm looking for.
>> M
>> um
and I found the tree, right? But between
me and the tree, there's like a huge
lake or like a gigantic water
>> like between me and the tree.
>> Yeah.
>> And there's no way for me to reach the
tree, right?
>> Yeah.
>> And so I'm standing there like gazing
the tree. I'm like I'm I'm trying to
figure out like figure out a way to to
to get to the tree and
and then like as I as I'm ging the tree
and I realize the the reflection of the
tree is like a it's like more vivid than
the tree itself on the reflection of the
tree on the water, right? And as as if
the reflection of the tree
is it's talking to me and then I heard
this voice uh and he and he said
uh stop looking outward start looking
inward and I'm always with you
and then w then I opened my eyes and
woke up and the first thought that came
to my mind is as above so below
>> and I'm still thinking about it. Yeah.
So, I just want to share this.
>> Yeah. That's beautiful dream. And
actually, it's very interesting. First
of all, how vivid the dream is, how
you're able to remember it so clearly
and vividly. That's pretty rare with
dreams. Second of all, what's really
interesting is like when Dante ascends
purgatory higher, he's going to have a
vision similar to your vision. Yes.
Where they're going to go meet a tree
and the tree is going to talk to them.
And um it's very interesting why this
happens. Does anyone want to try to
interpret his dream?
Try to try to think like why this is
happening. He see he sees a tree and he
thinks this tree is his goal, but
there's a river that blocks access to
the tree. So instead he sees a
reflection and this reflection talks to
him. Okay, that's a very vivid dream and
this is something that actually Dante,
it's a vision that Dante would have and
we'll see a vision very similar to this
in as we climb up Mount Purgatory. So,
what is this dream about? Uh, yes.
>> I'll just do a simple interpretation
from lines that I remember that we read.
I remember there was a line where it
said that the seed was more than the
plant that grows in the end.
>> Yes. And so maybe it's a reference that
it has to grow within you and you can't
seek out the finished plant. And then
another line was that um God's will is
on the other side of a river that no
human can damn. So maybe it's like the
flow of time, the flow of change, and
that you're so tempted to look on the
other side of the bank, but really you
just have to stay on your side and try
and think about it for yourself.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's great interpretation.
So um in purgatory uh Dante uses the
metaphor plant a lot. Okay. And usually
refers to family. So when he says plant
and seed it means just because you're
born as family does not does not
actually uh confine your fate. You're
still independent of this family. Okay.
The seed and the plant are not the same
thing. Okay. But he he uses the um
metaphor plant a lot to describe uh
family and also plant of course also
refers to the tree of knowledge. And so
the idea is we shouldn't be condemned to
original sin, right? Just because of
what Adam and Eve did. Okay. So, so
plant is a very important uh metaphor.
Plan and tree are very important
metaphors in uh purgatory. Any other
thoughts or interpretations?
Okay. So, as you read the divine comedy,
the um the interpretation will become a
lot more clear. Okay. All right. So, I
want to begin today's class by talking
about uh Yes.
Yes.
>> I have a question about the logistics of
purgatory.
>> Yes.
>> And um we have people moving up, but
let's use Pakarda as an example. So
Parda moved through purgatory and then
ended up in her spot.
>> Um so Picarda
actually went straight to heaven. Yeah.
She didn't actually go through purgatory
because she she live she lived a sinless
life, right? She was without sin. She
was was about blame.
>> So because I was under the impression
that maybe Elijah and Ilah who um I'm
getting they went straight to heaven.
>> They went straight to heaven. Yes. But
everybody else even everybody else is
has some sort of sin and so they went
through purgatory but okay. So Pard is a
bad example, but anybody else um who's
going to extend through purgatory, are
they going to snap instant end up in
their part of Paradisio that they expect
or I I didn't get any idea that we moved
through Paradisio also?
>> That's that's that that's a great
question. Okay, so the idea is there's
certain individuals who go straight to
heaven, right? These include Mary, um
Rachel, Ruth,
um Beatatrice
and so the um but in paradise there is a
hierarchy as well and the hierarchy um
is really your proximity to God and this
is determined by your understanding,
your faith, your willingness to be by
God. Okay. Okay. So the people who are
closest to God of course are people who
se who are seated in uh the red rose. Um
and
so the question then is okay let's think
of this. If you ascend through purgatory
um what determines your place in heaven?
Well, well, it would be the same
criteria, right? Because purgatory, it's
meant to purge you of your sins. But
once you're purged of your sins, then
what remains is your understanding of
God, your faith in God, and your
willingness to be to be in God. and
Picarda, she did she did lead a sinless
life, but it was one about um real
faith, right? So, it was kind of passive
and that that that showed a limited
understanding of God that showed limited
faith that that showed limited um
willingness to be God. So she did she
like she got she got to Yale so she did
all everything required checked all the
boxes but she's basically like the worst
student at Yale because she's not
willing to take the hardest classes you
know uh she you know she's not really
pushing herself to her limit. Okay. Does
that make sense? Okay. All right. All
right. So let's talk about the
schematics of um the divine comedy. So
we know from paradise because we had
paradise first
that um ultimately the end goal of the
universe is for us to co-create with
God. How? Through faith
uh hope
and love.
And what we also discussed is that faith
it's really about imagination.
Right? You have to imagine that God
exists. You have to imagine that God is
all loving, all generous, all merciful.
You have to imagine that you have a
special divine mission on earth. Okay,
this is all things that you cannot
prove. You just have to imagine them.
You have to believe them. Okay, that's
the idea of faith. Then hope is one of
arrogance which is to say like I matter.
What what I do on this earth matters and
and I could be a nobody right? It
doesn't matter. I still have
responsibility to uh love those around
me to seek justice uh to be generous
with others. Okay. Okay. So, think of
Rachel who didn't really do much, but
because
um because when presented with a choice,
right, Leah had already married uh
Jacob, she still chose to love Jacob and
marry him and like endure the pain of
being with her sister for the rest of
her life. Okay. So, that's the idea of
hope. And then love is one of action.
Okay. If you truly love someone, then
you will pray for this person for all
eternity. Okay. So, that's that's the
green grand um thesis that Donnie is
presenting. A a truly good life that
that draws you closer to God is one of
faith, hope, and love. And this counters
the traditional understanding of what
these terms meant historically as
presented by Paul and Augustine, right?
Um faith is one of compliance.
Don't question things, just believe
things. Hope is one of humility.
You are saved by the grace of God.
There's nothing you can do to change
your fate. Just just be humble before
God and then you will ascend to heaven.
And love is really one of obedience to
obey the church to to be a sheep and let
the church be the shepherd. Okay. So
again this framework um um subverts the
traditional church teachings. When we
went to inferno what we appreciated is
that the nine circles of hell are
designed in a way as to promote these
ideas on earth and to punish those who
subvert this these ideas. Okay. So as
you remember the the nine circles are
limbo
um lust
um gluttony,
greed
and anger. Okay. So these five are
outside the capital of hell this. So
they're not that serious.
Okay. And then within this um there's
heresy,
violence,
fraud, and then treachery.
Okay? And these [clears throat] are the
nine. And again, it makes sense because
um these four disrupt others capacity to
practice faith, love, and hope. Okay? So
right now we completely understand
what's going on. When we get to
purgatory, there are problems. Okay?
Because there are seven terraces now.
And these seven terrorists are
um [snorts] uh pride,
envy,
sloth,
um greed,
um
is it uh wrath,
uh lust, and then there's gluttony.
Okay. Actually, you know what? I I I I
think I think I screwed this up. I I I
think I I I I Anyway, um it doesn't
matter. Okay. All right. So, what we
also discuss is that um there are
certain punishments
that just would replicate themselves in
hell. Okay. So, for example, there's no
there's no circle of envy, but the
punishment is to be blindfolded to to be
blind. Basically, your eyes are shut and
you have to hold on to other people in
order to get around. Okay? and you have
to depend on other people to get around.
And this um is punishment for trying to
for envying other people. Okay? Because
before you saw yourself as separate from
other people, now you're completely
dependent on other people. Okay?
Um and in hell it' be the same thing.
But what we said is like the results
would be different because in uh
purgatory because they're depend because
they're trying to seek redemption.
They're trying to push themselves of
their envy. They're actually working
together, okay? And they're looking
inward to be a better person. Whereas in
hell, if this were the same situation,
then they would not work together. They
push each other around and they would
all imagine that each is better than
than than the rest. And because you're
blind, they can't see that they're
actually the same. They would go they
would go crazy. Okay? They would be very
angry. So the question for us is
how would this system
further this system? Okay, do you
understand? There's a totality, there's
a unity, a coherence to this Dante
cosmology. I'm trying to figure out the
logic of this. I understand why you'd be
punished for disrupting this the system,
but how would this actually help us get
to this? Okay.
All right. So, um so before I do that, I
just wanted to u basically summarize
what the punishment. Okay. So, for pride
um uh you have to learn humility, right?
So, what happens is like you are like
stones are put on top of you and you
have to like crawl. Okay. Okay. So,
you're always um humbled. Okay. Uh for
sloth, you you're you are forced to run
around a lot. Okay. You're you're
active. You're running around run a lot.
Um for greed, you're crawling. Okay. Why
you're crawling? Because before on
earth, you were so greedy, you wanted
power, right? So, you're always
ascending. But as punishment, now you
are crawling. Uh with wrath, what
happens is you're blinded by smoke.
And the idea is that your anger blinds
you, right? And so you have to learn to
see with your heart. Um gluttony is you
basically starve. [laughter]
You're starving. Uh lust is that you're
burning you're you're you're burned by a
flame. Okay.
So uh this is the structure of purgatory
and I want to figure out why it's like
this.
How would constructing a system like
this purgatory help advance the larger
goal of ensuring that everyone lives a
life of faith um hope and love? Any
suggestions?
Okay. So, first of all, is it easy to
get into purgatory?
Yeah, it's pretty easy. Okay. There are
lots of ways you you get into purgator
purgatory. Okay. So, one is to repent at
the last minute, right? You can live a a
life of total sin, but the very last
minute you're like, I seek God. Okay?
That's one way. Another way is if you do
an act of charity, an act of goodness in
your life once. Okay, that goes against
the church which is like if you do an
act of sin once, you're screwed. But
here it's like no, you do an act of good
once and then you're saved. Um your
family members could pray for you,
right? Um there are lots of ways to get
into into purgatory. So one me so one um
really interesting thing about purgatory
side it's easy to get into it's easy to
get into hard to advance.
Okay, does that make sense? Like anyone
can go to purgatory but to graduate you
have to like work really hard and it
could take you a million years. Okay,
that's the first characteristic about
purgatory.
Okay.
The second is
what else about what's another distinct
characteristic about about purgatory
that's important for us to appreciate.
>> Uh yes,
>> that if people pray for you then you
serve like long uh less time.
>> Exactly. Okay. People's prayers matter.
Okay. So you have to figure out who
prays for you, right? And we we
discussed yesterday I might have like 10
million fans. They're gonna pray for me
for all eternity when I die. Okay? So, I
better treat my kids and my parents and
my neighbors, my friends well because
they might pray for me but not my fans.
Okay. U so that's really important to
appreciate. Uh did you have a
>> that you can't look back otherwise it'll
go right back to the beginning.
>> Yes. Okay. You have to have conviction
and devotion. Okay. Yes.
The moment you go in, you have to commit
yourself to complete cleansing yourself.
The moment you doubt, you're out. You're
out of there. Okay. Uh yes.
>> No, I was going to say the same thing.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. So again, there
are some some uh any other curistic
about purgatory. Yes.
>> Uh just a question cuz you said uh if
you don't have the conviction, you get
out of there. But I thought in one of
the last classes you said everyone who
gets into purgatory will get out. No,
no, no, no. I said if you get into into
purgatory, you can now have the
opportunity to go to heaven, right? But
that doesn't mean you go automatically
to heaven because it's hard to graduate,
right?
Excuse me. But eventually, but as long
as you maintain your conviction, right?
The moment you're like, you know, I I
don't want to do this anymore, then
you're kicked out. Okay.
All right. Any more interesting
characteristic about purgatory?
Yes.
>> It requires cycles of self-reflection
and inward look. So the traveling by day
only, ascending by light.
>> Yes, that's right. That's right. The
self-reflection is very important.
Is there a hierarchy to purgatory?
There's a hierarchy to hell and heaven,
right? There's a hierarchy to purgatory.
There's really isn't a hierarchy, right?
Do you understand? There's really no
isn't saying like, oh, this like the
higher you go, the worse the sin or or
like the least the sin. Okay? It's all
equal. So, what happens is rather than
doing all seven terraces, you just do
one terrace, you fulfill your you purge
your sin and then you go straight to
heaven. Okay? So you just assign to one
um terrace and then that's that's good
enough. Okay. So there's it's just
basically uh
uh no hierarchy.
Okay. All right. So so explain to me why
purgatory is constructed the way it is.
And again we need to remember there's a
unity a totality to divine harmony. And
so all three have to line up perfectly,
right?
So, we've been to paradise. We know what
paradise is about. We've been to hell.
We know what we know what hell is about.
Explain what what purgatory is about.
>> Yes. Well, one thing it does, it um
inverses the sins of inferno or hell
because lust is uh at the very first in
inferno, but it's at the very top in
purgatory.
>> Yeah, it's really weird this way, right?
There there's an inversion going on,
right?
Yeah. No, the show is very clever this
way where in um inferno the the the four
sins,
lust, gluttony, greed, anger, they're
inverted in in purgatory.
Why Why would he do that?
Yes.
up the layer of the purgatory, you're
closer to heaven, so the sin is not as
severe as the ones at the bottom layers.
That's that's interesting. Okay, that's
an interesting idea, huh? But I don't
understand why. Oh, yeah, you're right,
actually. Yeah, this this does make
sense. Yes. Right. Okay. So, there there
is a hierarchy. Yeah, I'm wrong. Okay.
Yeah, because you're close to heaven and
this you're and then this is like
further from heaven. You're right. No,
no, no, no. You're right. Okay. Yes,
there is a hierarchy like the higher you
go, the less serious the uh the sin.
Yes.
>> Uh yes.
>> And it's very interesting that the
punishment is kind of the same except
it's the attitude of the partaker. So
then it's all about attitude and it's
all matching.
>> Right. Right. So I'm trying to figure
out but why? Okay. We're trying to
figure out the logic of this structure.
Okay. So, whenever we encounter a
situation where we're trying to figure
figure something out, okay, what we
always want to do is figure out the
counterfactual.
You understand? Okay. So, let's do the
counterfactual. Let's just say um we
don't do it this way and we just do it
the way the Catholic Church wants to do
it, right?
Okay, this is purgatory.
Someone explain to me what is being
taught about purgatory at this point in
history.
Okay. Um, yes.
>> That you'll be punished until you repent
and that
um it's like hell, but you suppose that
you'll feel bad enough that eventually
you'll turn to God because it's so
unhappy to be there.
>> Okay. Explain me who gets into hell, who
who gets in into purgatory according to
the Catholic Church after some ministry
by the year 1300. I think you can
basically buy your way into purgatory
through money or good deeds.
>> You understand? So what so what's really
important to understand is the church
determines who goes to purgatory. Okay,
>> right? That's number one. Number two is
for indulgences indulgences, the church
can also determine how long you stay in
in purgatory. Do you understand? So what
purgatory really is is a back door into
heaven,
right? So, you really screwed up, but
you're a trillionaire and you're like,
"Well, you know what? I'll give you $2."
And the church is like, "Fine. Then
we'll give you a back door into heaven."
Okay?
And uh as long as your
family continues to pay us off, then
we'll lessen your time in purgatory. Do
you understand? So, at this time in
history, purgatory is really a backdoor.
That's point one. Okay. What else about
purgatory at this point in history?
Do do you guys you guys remember? Yes,
>> I remember a lot of fire in the imagery.
Like there's just a lot of burning. So
the purging is like how you extract
finer metals from ore and and bad
substances.
>> Okay. So um what's really important to
appreciate is that uh before Dante
heaven hell to they were not actually
fleshed out. Okay. What what's genius
about Dant is that he actually does
flesh out them out into real worlds.
He's a worldmaker. He's a world builder.
But before that uh hell, purgatory and
heaven were just concepts. Right? So in
Augustine State of God he will say that
what heaven is is every day you're
seeing with God. Okay? which is a great
image but it's a concept it's not a
world whereas Donnie will actually build
the world okay so I'm just saying like
conceptually how is purgatory being
described at this time in history the
first is like it's really a backdoor
into heaven all right it's an escape
clause you should be burning in hell but
if you give us a trillion dollars we'll
put you in purgatory okay who else is
who else is in purgatory
infants Right. Okay. Infants.
So another way of saying this is like
this is a theological
loophole.
You guys you guys understand the idea
where if I can't actually explain
something using heaven and hell
purgatory. Okay. Well, I can't explain
babies who die, right? Because they're
innocent but they weren't baptized. So
they can't belong in he hell but they
don't belong in heaven either. So
purgatory. Okay. Do you guys understand
what's going on? Where? Like if if
there's ever a special case like I don't
know what's going on. Purgatory, right?
So at this time in history, purgatory is
not really developed.
Okay. And in in in reality, purgatory is
is only like a very special cases. But
what Donnie does is he turns purgatory
into another in a world equal to that of
hell and heaven. Right? And at this time
in history, most people aren't even
thinking of purgatory because you
because you you can't be that rich to
buy people place in purgatory, right?
You have to be rich. You have to provide
indulgences in order to get your
relative into purgatory. And so this
doesn't apply to most people, right?
So explain to me what the difference is
now.
Yes.
>> Um to tie it all together, I think the
fundamental message of Dante in the
divine comedy is on the heaven side,
right? It's it's it's it's unity, it's
faith, hope, and love. Fundamentally,
God is love, right? So that's a very
simple message. And then you try to
break it down. as you try to break it
down.
I guess what I take purgatory to mean is
that no matter which stage of purgatory
you're in, there's a fundamental lesson
to be learned. And if you learn that
lesson, it doesn't matter where you are
at in purgatory, you would be with
self-reflection, with prayer, with
conviction, you'd be able to learn that
fundamental truth and profile yourself
up to heaven. So I guess in my mind that
ties it all together. Um um whereas in
hell you're not you're not learning,
right? There's no growth mindset, right?
So that the real distinction is between
hell like the extremes of of uh of hell
and heaven. Purgatory is just the
process.
>> Okay. All right. So So let let's just
list the differences. Okay. The
difference between this and this is
first of all it's democratic.
It means anyone
everyone participates in the system.
Purgatory was designed for special
cases. Now it's like anyone, everyone
can participate. Okay? If you're poor,
you can still pray for your loved one in
purgatory,
right? Before you were poor, you were
screwed because you you didn't have
money to grab the church. So, first of
all, it's democratic where everyone can
participate. Okay, that's point one. Uh
point two is that it's really hopeful,
right?
where no matter how bad a person you
are, as long as you are willing to
repent or as long as someone really
loves you or you in the past did someone
a good favor, you would still be granted
access to purgatory. Okay? So, it's
hopeful. Whereas at this time in
history, uh the Catholic Church teaches
you uh not to have any hope. Okay? Don't
have hope. Just just believe in God. Uh
yes. And it's also action based rather
than having to pay money or
>> Exactly. Okay. So yeah, so it u
incentivizes action, right?
Whereas this system is really about
obedience, right? Incentivizes
obedience. Obey what the church says and
you'll be granted purgatory. Here it's
individual action, right? And the other
thing is that this is a much more
merciful and just system. Does that make
sense? Right? Because before the idea
was only a few people could access
heaven. Now it's like anyone everyone
can access heaven but you have to work
hard. Okay.
So
this is
um so this is a radically different
conception of purgatory. Explain why why
this has to be the case. Why does it
have to be democratic, hopeful um in
some of action and it has to be merciful
and just in order for this to be
unified?
Yes,
>> it's consistent with his cosmology that
God is love. Because if it's not
democratic, not everyone can
participate. It's only for the elite or
the rich, then the kingdom of heaven is
not for the poor like Jesus said in a
sermon on the mount.
>> Exactly.
>> And so everything has to confirm to
that.
>> That's right. Yes.
>> Yeah. That's also what I wanted to say.
And to uh add on to that, I feel like
for these different layers within
purgatory is also separated by no love
at the bottom which is like pride and
then like uh whatever and then like
going upwards is like not enough love
like I don't know like envy and etc. And
then at the end is like too much love.
>> Yes.
>> Than what you're supposed to have.
>> Exactly. You're right. Exactly. Right.
So the it structure the the sorry it
structure the way it is because this the
last four okay they it's really a like
misdirection of love right either too
much or too little love. Yes. Great.
All right. Anyone else? Yes.
Can we say the ego dissipates as we go
up? So pride you're loving yourself and
by the end uh greed, gluttony and lust.
You're loving the thing. Yes. instead of
and so you're getting less and less of
yourself.
>> Yes, exactly. That's that's great. Yes.
Uh yes.
>> Going back to the biatitudes, this would
be how the biatitudes would work because
>> the church almost at that time subverts
that.
>> Right. Right. Exactly. Yes. Any other
thoughts or comments? Yes.
>> I'm going back to a comment a really
smart person told me yesterday like why
why does envy exist? Right. like
somebody uh one of our classmates uh was
commented that um it's actually pretty
simple for you to get rid of envy if
you're sufficiently smart enough. Right?
So I'm I'm I'm looking at all these
things in purgatory and I'm I'm I'm
realizing like it's one and the same
like in in some sense all these
challenges that we have in purgatory is
because of the lack of love and the lack
of compassion and the lack of
imagination right so so um if we can I
know overcoming one is equivalent to
overcoming all of them
>> yes
>> I just thank you yes
>> um I've started to think about the whole
structure a little bit like um
physically structured like a Christmas
cracker.
>> Yes.
>> Where like there's a handle on either
side and God pulling one one up one way
and one the other way and that the
middle section is like a even cylinder
and the other two sections are like
mountains or in the top case like a V.
>> Yes.
>> And so I think this kind of explains how
there's a hierarchy but no hierarchy
that none of them are better than the
other. I want to ask if you think that
pride is the most fundamental
of the seven deadly sins. It's like the
father of the of sins.
>> Pride? Huh?
>> Okay. Can you can you can you do you
have an answer? Well, I think it's like
the bedrock of the other sins because
it's what fundamentally stops you from
um dealing with dealing with your
faults. I guess it's like arrog like the
bad form of arrogance.
>> Explain to me why pride leads to
laziness, sloth. because you believe
your innate ability requires less action
and energy to achieve your goals than
you than the truth than in reality. So,
um, but I don't really understand how
pride would give you wrath or pride
would give you gluttony. I mean, it just
seems like the basis for misdirection,
>> right? Yeah. So um so Don would not say
pride he would say ego right it's the
ego that's basis of everything so the
ego is basically how do you perceive
yourself do you take yourself seriously
right what do you think your role in the
universe is how much agency do you have
so the main thing undergirling
everything okay is the idea of free will
you guys understand this this this
cosmology construct the way it is to
ensure maximum free will. Okay,
this entire structure is designed so
like you at every point you have to
believe you have a choice.
Never ever must you believe that this is
God's will. There's nothing I can do
about it. Okay,
Don is trying to eliminate that
possibility. So the co cosmologist can
talk in a way
like you can reason everything out and
appreciate that it's your choice, not
God's choice. Okay?
Does that make sense? That's the real
purpose of this cosmology to coni
convince you it's always your choice.
It's always your free will. Everything
that happens is because of what you do.
Okay.
Yes. Would this kind of be in
contradiction to people like Anne Selmma
at the time who were really interested
in describing how God was outside of
time and that somehow his will was
already in the universe.
>> That's right. That's right. So again,
most theologians I would say every
theologian would say that's just absurd.
Like if we have all free will, what is
the function of God in the universe?
Right. What is God doing? I mean we
can't we I mean like it it would be so
arrogant to think that um we can do
whatever we want right so this goes goes
against church theology
um but this again is why this is a
radical revolutionary poem for its time
it's not so radical for us but for the
year 1300 this is revolutionary idea
like God is pure love pure love is to
gift you free will and free choice and
the entire cosmology ology is designed
to ensure maximum
agency, maximum free will. Okay? Does
that make sense, guys? All right.
All right. Let's uh go to candle 15 and
um I I want to do as much as possible
today. Okay. Because this is the um last
two days, okay? Believe it or not, we we
we we've been doing this for a long
time, right?
>> 10 days.
>> 10 days. Okay.
>> Uh and and how how long does it feel to
you guys?
>> Does it feel does it feel like a long
time?
>> Okay. Yes.
[clears throat] Just a comment because I
remember I read this in that same
manipul piece. But he summarizes uh the
sins of purgatory I think quite nicely
and he says that the first three sins
[clears throat] are the effect of love
perverted. The last three are profane,
love, excessive, and the middle one,
sloth, is love, defective.
>> That's right. Exactly. Yes. Okay.
Exactly. So, it has to do all has to do
with love. Um, great. Thank you so much.
Okay. Um, also I want to apologize uh to
everyone like not learning your names.
I'm terrible with names and I knew that
there was going to be some shifting over
the course of these um um two weeks. But
now it's second last day. I want to
learn your names. I I want to get to
know you better. Okay. All right. So um
when I call on you, please please let
you let me know your name. All right. So
this is um candle 15. Okay.
As many as the hours in which the sphere
that's always playing like a child
appears from daybreak to the end of the
third hour, so many were the hours of
light still left before the course of
day had reached sunset. Vespers was
there and where we are midnight. When
sunlight struck directly at our faces,
for we had circled so much of the
mountain that now we headed straight
into the west. Then I could feel my
vision overcome by radiance greater than
I'd sensed before. And unaccounted
things left me amazed at which that they
might serve me as a shade. I lifted up
my hands above my brow to limit some of
that excessive splendor. As when a ray
of light from water or mirror lapses in
the opposed direction and rises at an
angle equal to its angle of descent, and
to each side the distance from the
vertical is equal, as science and
experiment have shown. So did it seem to
me that I had been struck there by light
reflected facing me at which my eyes
turned elsewhere rapidly. Kind father,
what is that against which I have tried
in vain? I said to screen my eyes it
seems to move toward us. And he replied,
don't wonder if you're still dazzled by
the family of heaven. A messenger has
come and he invites us to ascend. Soon
in the sight of such things, there will
be no difficulty for you, but delight as
much as nature fashioned you to feel. No
sooner had we reached the blessed angel
than with glad voice he told us enter
here these are less steep than were the
other stairs.
>> Um so what's happening is that um now
and then Donnie is getting blinded. Why?
Because an angel that is so radiant is
coming down and to basically remove a
pee from his forehead and allow him to
ascend further. And it seems like doc
Virgil knows all this right? Do you
understand the paradox here where Virgil
he is a pagan and he um has been in
limbo all his life but he knows all how
all this works.
He knows the entire structure of
purgatory as well as uh infernal. Why is
this the case?
>> Yes.
>> Because he had the divine spark in him
of the poet.
>> That's right. Even though he chose to
pervert
>> he that that's exactly right. Okay. So
this is something that you guys must
appreciate. All poets are prophets. All
prophets are poets. Jesus was a poet. If
you read his um quotations from in the
Bible, it's poetry. Okay. Uh yes.
>> Then why doesn't Dante know the way?
>> Excuse me.
>> Why doesn't Dante know the way? Because
Dante is also a poet.
>> Who says he doesn't know the way?
He keeps asking questions.
>> Um, okay.
Let's think think about this. Okay. Why
does he So, let's just assume he Don is
a poet. He knows everything. Why? Why
does he need Virgil to guide him?
Explain this to me.
Yes.
I think he
I think people do this for themselves.
Like when you talk to yourself, it's
similar to that where you need an
outside other entity to try and talk to
you. And it's like your inner voice is
giving you instructions. So you need to
give that inner voice a being and a body
of some kind so that it's stops you
against pride or arrogance that it's you
doing it.
>> Yeah. So, I mean, if you go to the gym,
everyone knows how to work out, right?
Like, you just watch YouTube videos and
it'll tell you exactly how to work out.
Why do you need a trainer,
right? Is a trainer going to really add
knowledge to your routine? Probably not.
But your trainer is just going to tell
you like just focus, right? That's all
the trainers say, focus, focus, focus.
That's what Virgil is doing. He's saying
focus, focus, focus. Right?
All right. Does that make sense? So um
Donnie would not be on this journey
unless he was a poet. Unless he were a
poet. Okay, keep on going.
Line 37. We climbed already past that
point. Behind us we heard Bayati
Merordes sung and then rejoice you who
have overcome. I and my master journeyed
on alone. We two together upward as we
walked. I thought I'd gather profit from
his words. And even as I turned toward
him, I asked, "What did the spirit of
Romana mean when he said sharing cannot
have a part?" And his reply, "He knows
the harm that lies in his worst vice. If
he chastises it to ease its experation,
do not wonder.
For when your longing center on things
such that sharing them a portionsless to
each, then envy stirs the bellows of
your size. But if the love within the
highest sphere should turn your longings
heavenward, the fear inhabiting your
breast would disappear. For there the
more there are who should say ours so
much the greater is the good possessed
by each. So much more love burns in that
cloister. I'm more hungry now for
satisfaction, I said, than if I'd held
my tongue before. I host a deeper doubt
within my mind. How can a good that's
shared by more possessors enable each to
be more rich in it than if that good had
been possessed by few? and heed to me.
But if you still persist in letting your
mind makes on earthly things, then even
from true light you gather darkness. The
good, ineffable and infinite which is
above directs itself toward love as
light directs itself to polished bodies.
Where order is that good gives of
itself, and where more love is there,
that good confers a greater measure of
eternal worth. And when there are more
souls above who love, there's more to
love well there, and they love more a
mirror like each soul reflects the
other. And if my speech has not appeased
your hunger, you will see beatus. She
will fulfill this and all other longings
that you feel now only strive so that
the other five wounds may be canceled
quickly as the two already are. The
wounds contrition heals.
>> Okay, so Virgil is just telling us what
we'll learn in paradise, right? Like the
unifying force of the universe is love.
The more we love, the more God glows in
in us. And so if we turn away from
material obsessions
then we will recognize this and we will
create more and more love in the world.
So love can be infinite but wealth has
to be finite. Okay. Um okay keep on
reading
>> line 82. But wanting then to say you
have appeased me. I saw that I had
reached another circle and my desiring
eyes made me keep still. There I see him
suddenly to be caught up in an ecstatic
vision and to see some people in temple
and a woman just as the threshold in the
gentle manner that mothers use was
saying, "Oh my son, why have you done
this to us? You can see how we have
sought you sorrowing your father and I."
And at this point, as she fell still,
what had appeared at first now
disappeared. Then there appeared to me
another woman upon her cheeks the tears
that grief distills when it is born of
much scorn for another. She said, "If
you're ruler of that city to name which
even goddesses once pride, where every
science had its source of light, revenge
yourself on the presumptuous arms that
embrace our daughters, oh pisitus, and
her lord seems to mean benign and mild."
His aspect temperate as he replied,
"What shall we do to one who injure us
if one who loves us earns our
condemnation?" Next, I saw people whom
the fire wrath had kindled and they
stoned at youth and kept on shouting
loudly to each other, "Kill, kill,
kill." I saw him now down by death sink
to the ground. Although his eyes were
bent, but were always on heaven, they
were heaven's gates. Praying to his high
lord despite the torture to pardon those
who were his persecutors. His wolf was
such that and lofted compassion.
And when my soul returned outside itself
and that met the things outside it that
are real, I then could recognize my not
false error.
>> Okay, stop. Okay. All right. So, uh
there are three stories here. Okay. The
first story is from the gospel of Luke
where um Mary and Joseph they lose Jesus
when Jesus is 12. And and and why do do
you guys remember the gospel of Luke?
Where's Jesus when when he's 12 years
old? Uh yes. Sorry. What was your name?
>> I'm Anna.
>> Yes. So he went to the temple to debate
or argue with or teach the rabbis, the
teachers of the law, and they were
amazed by his genius. That's right. And
then it was at the end of a wedding
feast. So the parents were probably busy
with the guest and then they couldn't
find him and they found him finally.
>> Yeah. Like where are you?
>> Yeah. So this is a story from the Gospel
of Luke. And you can imagine how angry
Mary is at him, right? It's like you
know, you had us worried. We thought you
were lost, but it turned out no you
there's there's nothing to worry about.
There's nothing to be angry about. Jesus
is just being Jesus. Okay. The second
story comes to us from Athens where the
wife or the ruler of Athens is angry
that um like a a a man is chasing their
daughter and begging her for marriage.
And the wife is like how presumptuous
this man is. He is beneath us. So we
should punish him. And then Pac Piderus
the the king.
Why are we punishing someone who
flatters us? Right? Isn't he flattering
us that we that um he wants our daughter
in marriage? And if people who are nice
to us we punish then people who are mean
to us what do we deal with? Okay. All
right. So it shows the the ignorance of
wrath of anger. And the last example is
also from the Bible the story of St.
Steven who is stoned to death for
idolatry by the um Jews in Jerusalem.
Okay, he was the first martyr of the
Christian tradition. You will find this
in the acts of the apostles and rather
than uh be angry what uh Steven does is
pray for their forgiveness. Okay. All
right. So these are three examples of
how to deal with wrath. Okay.
Understanding
um and forgiveness.
What are these things?
How how does see these things?
>> Excuse me.
>> But I'm saying like how does he actually
see these things? Yes. kind of like the
artworks maybe of
>> priorities. It's similar to the artwork,
right? But are these artworks?
>> These are movies kind of like visions
because they disappear after a while.
>> No, no, like like But how does he see
them
before? How did he have his visions?
>> Dream.
>> Dreaming was the first, right? Then it
was the artwork. Right now, what's
happening?
It's like the ecstatic visions of St.
Teresa.
>> These are daydreams. You guys
understand? He's actually seeing them as
he walks.
All right, this is like lucid
daydreaming.
How does this happen? Okay, we
understand how dreams work. We
understand how
artwork works, right? We we spend all
time discussing artwork, but how does
this work? You just have visions like
you're just walking through. Wow. Like I
have this image in my head,
right? Yes. Oh, sorry. So, what's your
name?
>> Uh, Fred.
>> Fred. Okay. Yes.
>> Um, I guess it's like reflected light. I
don't want to say like psychedelics, but
the the Kantos kind of start where he's
saying, "I'm trying to cover my eyes,
but the light's bouncing in no matter
what." So, it's kind of like it's
impossible for him not to see it.
The mechanism is very mysterious. I
still think though.
>> Okay, it's possible. Okay, but that
makes no sense. Reflected light, doesn't
it blind you? I mean, I I guess it
blinds him and then he has these
visions, right? But but again, like
where are these visions coming from? We
understand the artwork. We understand
the dreams. The dreams is from heaven.
Yes.
>> Um maybe it's just imagination, but it's
is um it's another level is high at a
higher level of imagination. Anyone
else?
It is definitely imagination, but I'm
like I'm I'm trying to figure out how
this works.
Okay. So,
um we we we will spend a lot of time
discussing this idea. Okay. Um so, we're
trying to figure out how the mind works
today. Okay. And who studed psychology?
Okay. You studied psychology, right?
How how do we have memories? Do tell us.
>> There's like the short-term and
long-term memories. And so there's a
transfer between so first you have the
knowledge that's going into your brain
and it sucks like very shortly
>> and then through a process of um
rethinking of it. So basically it's very
like loose memory in the short term and
then it goes to the long term and you
need to work on it back and forth for it
to strengthen.
>> Okay. Right. So so what is your name?
>> Uh Franel.
>> Franel. Okay. Okay. Um so let me explain
the neuroscience. Okay. What
neuroscientists believe how memory
works. Okay. So the idea is you have in
the beginning okay short-term memory
the short-term memory is filtered
through your senses
um into
um
long-term memory
and how the memory is then dealt with is
that it's divided into categories
determined by emotions. Okay, do you
understand? So if the emotion is anger,
it goes in the anger box. If it's happy,
it goes in happy box. And then if it's
sad, it goes in sad box, right? It's
basically just emotions. So your all
your memories are categorized by their
emotional value.
And then based on
um the
uh order of your emotions, this then
leads to your world view, okay? or your
identity.
[snorts]
Um and then that becomes part of your
senses which then determines what
memories you uh remember, what memories
you don't remember. Okay? So in other
words, uh first of all, you only
remember things that have emotional
value. Okay. It's why in school you
actually don't remember what you learn
in the classroom, but you remember a lot
what you did with your friends. Okay.
Yes.
two types where there is one linked to
emotions and one like only to knowledge
but it's right it's harder to remember
it
>> that's right that's right
>> but there is two categories
>> you're going to use brute force to to
>> okay yeah exactly okay
>> and because there is no recall also then
it's just hard to remember it
>> yes
>> if you learn math and you never think of
math and
>> that's right okay all right so uh yeah
so the memories are into emotional
values you remember what has emotional
value unless you use rot memorization to
remember useless facts like mathematics.
Okay. Um and the entire point is to
develop your world view. And why is
worldview important? Because it tells
you your place in society, right? It
tells you who you are and what your
relationship is with other people. It
helps you navigate. Okay. So, so really
this entire system is designed for us to
be social animals to interact with
others, to work with others, to compete
with others. Okay. All right. Yes.
>> I'm Andy.
>> Hi, Andy. So in this process would you
call the unconscious like
uncatategorized
things that are seeping into our dreams
or would you call it like the the divine
speaking to us?
>> Okay. Yeah. So again this is
neuroscience. Okay. Uh they do divide
between a conscious and a subconscious.
Right. Subconscious. The conscious is
this decision- making
whereas subconscious determines your
action.
Okay. So what neuros say is like we are
um conscious robots. Okay. We have
actually no control of ourselves but we
think we do. Okay. We we we just
rationalize our actions but it's the
emotions that determine our actions.
Okay. So who you are is your
subconscious not really your conscious.
Who you think you are is not really who
you are. Okay. So this is from
neuroscience. Are are we clear about
this? Okay. Um
this creates a lot of problems right
because obviously you're like okay if
this is the case where does the
imagination come from? And how is it
that people like Dante and Virgil and
Shakespeare, they're able to create
characters that are realistic and which
is not part of their emotional
experience. Like how does that work?
Right? If everything is stored in your
brain and you can only know what you
experience, then how how does Dante know
Virgil? Does that make sense? Yes.
>> I I'm I'm just going along with the
neuroscience explanation. Neuroscience
would say that they're able to simulate
these characters in their kind of own
networks and talk to them. Talk to the
simulation.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> It's go going a bit far, but you can I
think you can I'd never read of it, but
you can prime yourself with imagination.
And if you look and read a lot of books,
look at art, then just it opens your
mind into creating stuff. And maybe the
more you see new things then the more
you're able to create stuff.
>> Okay, I understand. Okay, but all you're
telling me is like Virgil is a
projection of Dante, right? Virgil
exists within Dante's larger
imagination. But if we read the but what
we're doing is we're reading the divine
comedy and we see Virgil as a completely
different person from Dante with his own
contradictions with his own worldview.
Right?
And if you read Shakespeare, you also
have people like that. In Shakespeare,
you have Hamlet. Uh you have they all
characters are distinct individuals. So
if they are all just projections of
Shakespeare, I don't know how that
works. Uh
>> uh I'm Edward.
>> Yes.
>> Um somehow he's managed to plug himself
into the collective consciousness.
>> Yeah, that's what I think. Okay, we
we'll talk more about this later. Okay.
But but but yes
>> and just one more thing is that I think
the reason why he's able to um simulate
ver create Virgil so well is that if you
imagine like the subconscious the the
field of consciousness of the universe
is like play-doh or clay when he's
reading the anerid a lot and it's almost
like he's feeling in closer and closer
detail the sculpture that is the anerid
and so when he's really reading it he
feels these thumbrints, these grooves of
the nail where he's able to see the
human mind of Virgil as you say by
reading the Anid so closely that he's
able to see feel the poet behind the
words and therefore have such a deep
empathy for him that the empathy creates
like a bubble of another being and that
that's how he plugs in.
>> Okay, that's a very logical explanation.
I don't think that's that's what's
happening. I don't think he's creating
Virgil. I think he's summoning Virgil.
There's a difference. You guys
understand there's there there's you can
create Virgil, right? using the same
process that you just described and
that's very logical but I think what's
happening is that he summoned Virgil
because to me I can't I've read the
Iniad
and I don't think the Virgil in the
Divine Comedy can be extrapolated from
reading the Iniad alone because there is
because Virgil if you read Virgil and
like you just hear the way he speaks
right it's it's like it feels like a
real person and why it feels like a real
person is
the contradictions, the nuance, the
subtlety cannot be created by you alone.
You have to summon this person. Does
that make sense? So, it's like he's it's
like he spent his entire life with
Virgil as his best friend and they're
just talking to each other all the time.
So, he understands this guy's
peculiarities, right?
Does that make sense? There's certain
things, there's certain qu corks that
like you cannot imagine it, you cannot
create it. It just has to be that
person. Yes,
>> it just reminds me when I was reading
about Machaveli, there was at the time
some guy called Valentino Borgger. Um,
he got a letter of recommendation where
this guy wrote that he was the
reincarnation of Thomas Aquinus and it
made the Catholic Church really, really
afraid because they didn't want anybody
to know about summoning angels and
demons and stuff.
>> Yeah, I think Don has summoned Virgil
here. It's very hard for me to explain
how this could work otherwise. Okay?
Because like we're reading the
relationship between Donnie and Virgil
very closely, right? And like I'm not
finding a contradiction in Virgil. Do
you understand? Right. And like we're
able to go into the very psychology of
Virgil as an independent actor, right?
where it will say like if Donn is doing
this then this is Virgil's response
and it matches perfectly with the text.
Yes.
>> Oh friend that Dente was friend with and
then he just wrote Virgil and his name.
It's what I imagine. Same for Beatatric
you know like it's so real that I think
it's actually a friend in real life just
transferred a name.
Um that is also a possibility. But then
you raise the question of like how does
the Virgil that is created right? How
how does the Virgil in Divine comedy how
does it match perfectly with the Virgil
who wrote the Iniad? Do you understand?
Because when we talk to Virgil you read
the Iniad you're like okay this is the
guy who wrote the the Iniad. Right?
Because when you read read the Iniad,
what you're reading is the persona of
Virgil who wrote the Iniad.
Okay? Does that make sense? Because
remember in divine com there are three
Dantes, right? There's Dante the
pilgrim, the character. There's Dante
the historical person, the real person.
There's D the poet. And all three are
different because Dante the pilgrim
obviously is the protagonist. Dante the
real person is a real person. But Dante
the poet is a person who is trying to
talk to us. You understand? Okay. So,
he's trying to create the ding comment
in a way that speaks to us
and I don't know how you do that unless
you're a real person. Okay. Whereas and
in in Virgil, yes, if you if you think
about Virgil and you were to bring him
outside and like ask him about the Inad,
he would know the Iniad like intimately,
right? He's like, "Yeah, it's obviously
he wrote he wrote the Iniad."
So, you're all providing good theories
and hypothesis,
but I mean, having thought very deeply
about this, I think he just summoned
Virgil. And this is like the real
Virgil, right? And this is absurd
because Donnie lived around the year
1300 and Virgil lived the year about
like, you know, during the time of
Jesus, like like uh not time of Jesus,
but but a generation before. Okay. So,
we're talking like 1300 years
difference. How's this possible? Uh yes.
>> Uh yeah, you know I think this uh Virgil
is uh just usher right. So I think Danny
have read a lot of thing about R uh
Virgil. So maybe they just imagine this
the role in his mind just like reason
because sometime we need to think about
something by reason and not by emotion
>> but emotion. So
>> so I write novels. Okay. I write novels.
Okay. And I I'll tell I'll I'll tell you
my writing process.
Um, what happens is I get up in the
morning and I have visions and I'm like,
I need to write these visions down and
hon and like if I don't write these
visions down, then I'm just going to be
haunted for the rest of my life. So,
I'll just write these visions down and
I'll be left alone. So, I write these
visions down. Okay? And when I'm writing
these visions, I don't know what
happens. It feel like I'm when I'm
writing, it feels like someone's taking
possession of me and I'm just writing
things. And then I'm writing about these
characters and I'm like I don't know
these people. Okay. It's it's it's like
it's it's not like I'm creating these
people. It's like these are being
revealed to me. And then um I finished
writing and I I look at these characters
like I don't know these people. I've
never met these people and they feel
real to me. But not only that, but I
feel as though these characters not only
are talking to me, but they're talking
to themselves independently.
Okay. And then and I'm exhausted after a
day's work and I fall asleep and like,
okay, well, my mind is blank and I'm not
going to have any more visions. Now, in
the morning, I get up again and I have
more visions. Okay? And then I keep on
working and then at the end of my novel,
what happens is like I look back and
it's like, how is it possible for me to
world build? Okay. How is it possible
for me to create all these people that
are independent of each other, have
different personalities, but they are
true to themselves, and they're true to
each other. Okay? And I'm like, I don't
know these people. I've never had this
in my own my life.
And like, I can't explain the process.
And that's why I think that what's
happened here is that Don has summoned
Virgil because these are two very
different people. They're alike in some
ways, but they're two different people.
Okay.
All right. So now what I'm going to do
is I'm I'm going to present another
theory of how this works. Okay.
And this is more in line with Dante's
theory of how this works. So So we know
the door of science. Okay. This is a
standard theory of memory and identity.
Right. Right. I mean this this is what
you're taught in school. Okay. Now I'm
going to present to you a different
theory. Okay. All right. So for Dante we
have the divine spark. The divine spark
is not a light in us. It's our soul. And
our soul is not um a part of us. It is
it is us. It's it's basically like our
electrical field. Okay? It it's it's an
aura around us. Okay? That's the real
soul. Okay? [snorts] Um and the soul
doesn't exist in our dimension. It
exists in different dimensions.
All right?
Um, and we also know from Dante that
there is a god and this god is the
emanation of the universe, the source of
the universe and we're all connected to
to this god. Okay, so the entire cosmos
is connected. Okay, so imagine um the
cosmos as this infinite
eternal
mind. Okay.
And what happens is that when we have an
emotion,
okay, the emotions aren't stored inside
our brains. They're stored inside this
universal consciousness as what Carl
Young would say, as what Manny Hall
would say. Okay. Right. Do first of all,
Edward, do do you want to explain to us
the theory before I I explain it myself?
I think it's it's just where you're
going that there's this idea that rather
than the the memories are stored in our
physical beings there is some a
collective consciousness and through uh
different methods uh that some people
propose there is a way of uh channeling
this and I don't know the exact um
stories of it but I know that there for
example even in in sort of the
contemporary world there are some
sources about for example like your very
young children that have knowledge of
things that there there is no way that
they would have known happen.
>> So people really can't explain this. Uh
so this is a separate theory that's
>> Yeah.
>> So so my eldest son Chris who who you
met and you guys met him as well cuz he
came in and like just you know walked
around. But when he was 2 years old he
told us mom dad I'm an alien from
another planet. Like okay we believe
you. We really do. Okay. Because when we
because we've seen him and he's like
he's not like me. He's not his mother.
He's he's his own person. And like when
he was two years old, he he told he told
us he's from another planet. So the
first thing we asked him, of course, is
like what planet? And he mentioned the
name. I can't remember it, but like for
him it was real. Okay. So it seems as
though like he came in with already
memories of a past life and possibly
many many past lives. I'm not sure if
you had a similar experience with your
children, but you know.
>> Yeah. Like like no my they're aliens.
Yes. Okay. So um yeah back to this here
okay so there is a universal
consciousness okay and think of it as an
infinite eternal grid so what happens is
that when we have emotions they're not
stored inside the brain they're stored
inside this universal mind okay and
there and these memories go in different
different locations so so if it's a bad
memory like a bad emotion hate then it
might be lower but but if it's a a good
emotion like happiness and joy bliss
then it's probably higher and higher in
the place. Okay.
Okay. So, this is this is where the
memories are stored. Okay. But not only
that, but Evelyn's memories are stored
here, right? So, it's like it's like the
internet. And so what happens is that
over time certain regions become like
alive themselves because they are being
uh because there's so much memories
being stored in this place, right? It
becomes alive itself and that's where
where we get the idea of like ghosts and
spirits and demons.
Okay? And so in other words, what
happens is like when we have memories,
okay, not only do we store the memories
in a certain place, but this place also
communicates, connects with us,
okay?
And so um
so basically you you're an independent
person but also you're a collection of
different memories from different eras
which means you're also a collection of
different individuals from different
times. Does that make sense? Okay. Why
is this important? Because now gives us
insight into how art works. Right?
Because what art really is, it is a
portal or a mechanism to enhance your
connection to this universal
consciousness, this internet. Okay? Does
it make sense? Okay. So when that
happens, then not only do you feel more,
but you feel more. Remember these
emotions come with their own memories,
with their own visions. Then these
visions come available to you. Okay? So
that's what art and dreaming does. It
connects you to this universal web. But
if the connection is really strong, then
you don't need these uh agents to
provoke you. You just see them yourself.
And so that's what's happened happened
to Dante. So what's happened is like he
um he's now able to see these visions
for himself without um artwork. And the
reason why he's able to see them, what
has given him sight is the fact that
he's cleansing himself of his sins,
right? Because you see sins, what sins
really do is they bulk you down to
material world and they make you forget
the universal truth, right? Which is the
universal consciousness. So the more
virtuous a life you you live, the more
visions you have because the greater
your connection to the divine.
All right,
do you guys understand this?
Any questions about this theory?
Yes.
>> But uh I understand you can uh summon
this um historical figures into your
mind. Um
it's like a seance, right? Uh but what
but can you like summon this like
fictional characters like let's say
you're writing a you're writing a novel,
right? And and these characters they're
not they do not existed in the they
didn't exist in the in the real world,
right? So, can you summon like fictional
characters?
>> What? But I mean like like this is an
infinite universe, right? There's
infinite people. So, so when you're
writing fiction, all you're doing is
you're summoning someone from from here.
Yes.
>> Also, just to answer that through
through this lens, like the fictional
characters uh are basically real
characters. Like they're not really
That's right. Like we're all sort of
part of the same
>> collection of archetypes.
>> Yes. Because when we read fiction, we're
we read it because it's real to us,
right? Because explaining these
universal truths to us. Uh yes.
[clears throat]
>> So does that mean whenever a person
writes a novel and the characters in
their novel um is sum summited
>> if he's a good writer. Yeah. But he
could be a bad writer in which case he's
just making crap up. Okay. But but how's
the the difference like the um why do
some writers write a good novel novel
and others write a bad novel?
>> Because like the writer has different
connection to the divine. Okay? Like no
no no it's really simple. Okay? You if
you choose to be a writer, you're
probably a crappy writer. You
understand? It's like I want to be a
writer and be I want to be famous.
You're probably a crappy writer. Okay?
If you're a good writer, you're just
born that way.
I I hate to say this, okay? Writers are
not uh writers are chosen by God. Dante
was chosen. Virgil was chosen. Too bad.
Okay. Uh yes.
Act of feeling lighter. I feel like when
you're lighter, your ideas come from a
spiritual world. Whereas if you're
really heavy, then it's just like
material like, "Oh, I'm lacking money or
I'm I'm late." And so there's really a
link into feeling lighter and having
better ideas.
>> That's exactly right. Yes. Remember in
so sorry so sorry so sorry so sorry so
sorry so sorry so sorry so sorry so
sorry sorry sorry sorry sorry sorry
sorry sorry uh Anna uh sorry so let me
respond to this and and then um so
remember how how in hell the lowest
level is Lucifer right and he's become a
machine so he's lost all consciousness
because he's lost the connection to this
universal consciousness right uh yes
>> but I have a problem with this theory
because in that way then it's like
Ecclesiastes there's nothing new under
the son everything we write in fiction
is a real person in the past. So then we
actually lost our imagination because we
don't create anything new.
>> So Carol's shaking her head. Yes.
>> Uhhuh. But oh okay.
So like all this collective
consciousness memories are not from
>> there's no time.
>> No time in space.
>> Oh okay. Right.
>> This is this is all the past. It's also
the future.
>> Oh I see. I see.
>> Okay. Okay. Because otherwise explain to
me how Dante is able to have such
revolutionary ideas in his time. Right?
>> Because like these ideas that he's
presenting never existed before. So what
he's done is he's looked into the
future.
>> Okay.
>> Right. Okay. Does it make sense guys?
Okay. So again what's really important
is as Carol says this is beyond time and
space. Okay. This is literally God.
Okay. This system. Okay. God is the
alpha and the omega, the beginning and
the end, everything that was and
everything that will be. Okay. So, when
you actually access the system, not only
are you accessing the past, but you're
also accessing the future.
Okay. Yeah.
Uh, but do you have like a better
imagery for like your concept? Because
it's really hard to write down what you
did here.
Like do you have a better way to like do
a drawing about like what's happening
with like bubbles or stuff?
>> Let's Google this. Okay. It's called
Indra's Pearl. Can you Google this,
please? Indra
Pearl.
Okay. All right.
Uh
uh or Android web. Is that that
>> web?
Okay. Just this.
Yeah. Does this make more sense to you?
The web
Since you've studied the brain,
sinapsies, right? Sinapses, neurons,
neuro connections.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, the idea is that God is with
is within us and we are within God. Does
that make sense?
That's that's a trick to understand that
we are it's hard to draw because both
are both are true at the same time,
right? We are we are within God and God
is within us. So the universe is within
us
>> when you
>> and we are the universe.
>> When you draw you would collapse it into
two dimension which is which is not.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Also you you need this fractalss right
fractal. So you are just a fractal of
the universe and what what's a fractal?
Fractal is just a reflection of the
universe, right? So within you is the
universe itself and but you're also a
part of the universe. God is in you and
you are inside God.
Okay? Does it make sense guys? All
right. This is really important because
once you know this then the rest of
Dante uh is is easier to understand.
Okay. But but the point is like now that
he has this connection to the vine
because he's inspired by art work. He's
committed to change and because he's
cleansing himself of more and more sins,
the visions will become much more
vibrant. Okay.
Okay.
Okay. Yeah. This this actually what I
wanted. Okay. You guys see this? Okay.
This is the best we can probably do. You
are inside God. God is inside you.
You guys do you guys see this? Yes.
I was just going to say also bringing it
more to uh contemporary thought like
we're talking about how Dante can clean
him clean himself
get better uh connection to the
collective conscious but it's also quite
similar to in Hinduism and in yoga when
they have the idea of kundalini right
that if you abstain from all these
desires you do very deep meditation over
years and years
>> yes
>> many people reported that they have
these visions and
>> that's right
>> connections to this highc Exactly.
Exactly. I mean, this is just a
universal truth. Okay. It's something
that I've experienced in my life where
um when I write novels, like I just
don't I don't create. I just, you know,
channel. If you if you if you create um
honestly, you're you're probably not
very good. So so so let me tell you a
funny story. Um so, uh my mentor is Ev,
but also Gay. Gay is one of the most
famous writers in America. He's 94 years
old and we were 25 years ago. We were we
were on a cruise ship in Shanghai and
there was three of us. There was Galiss
his wife Nantles who is one of the most
famous publishers in America. She
published Margaret Atwood and um all
these famous writers including Joan
Ddian and um she was telling us how Phil
Knight you guys know who Phil Phil
Knight is right a billionaire.
>> Nike. Yeah. He's found of Nike and and
she was telling us how obsessed
Phil Knight is with writing a book. In
fact, Phil Knight would just come to her
office every single day and sit there
for like two hours just to meet her and
talk to her talk to her about the book
he wants to write. And Natalie is like
he is awful. He's like the worst writer
ever. Okay. Um um but I mean imagine he
did publish a book. It's called Shoe Dog
and it's it's a bestseller. But, you
know, he's he's the richest he's one of
the richest men in the world. And he's
like, you know, I want to be a writer.
And he spent, you know, these decades
going to like these workshops, hiring
writers, learning the craft, but but
then Niss is like, you know, um he's not
a very good writer, but he is just so
joyful and enthusiastic and happy about
writing. He says he wants to write
because it brings him tremendous joy.
And then Gay Lee said, "Well, if you're
really stupid, you could be very happy
as a writer." Okay. All right. True
story. Um, like if you just suck, you
would find tremendous pleasure in
writing. But if you're really good, you
would find only agony and suffering in
writing because uh you recognize that
when you write, uh, you're not actually
in control. Okay? You're you're being
possessed. You're you're channeling.
Okay? Right? Does it make sense to you
guys? All
right. All right. Let's continue.
>> Line 115th. And when my soul returned
outside itself and met the things
outside it that are real, I then could
recognize my not false errors. My guide
on seeing me behave as if I were a man
who's freed himself from sleep, what's
wrong with you? You can't walk straight.
For more than half a league now you have
moved with clouded eyes and lurching
legs as if you were a man whom wine or
sleep has gripped.
Oh,
>> oh my kind father, if you hear me out,
I'll tell you what pured to me, I said,
when I had lost the right youth of my
leg, and he, although you had a hund
masks upon your face, that still would
not conceal for me the thoughts you
thought, however slight. What you have
seen was shown, lest you refuse to open
your heart unto the waters of peace that
pour from the eternal fountain. I did
not ask what's wrong with you. As one
who only sees with earthly earthly eyes,
which ones the body stripped of soul
lies dead can't see. I asked so that
your feet might find more force, so must
one urge the indolent. Too slow to use
their waking time when it returns. We
made our way until the end of vespers,
peering as far ahead as sight could
stretch. at rays of light that although
late were bright but gradually smoke as
black as night began to overtake us and
there was no place where we could have
avoided it
of pure air and sight.
>> Okay. So we uh were in the terrace of
law but they're all so busy you don't
have time to talk. Okay. Now moving up
to the terrace of wrath and and the
thing about the wrath uh ter of wrap is
all black smoke. Okay. [snorts] All
right. My way.
>> Kanto 16. [clears throat]
Darkness of hell and of a night deprived
of every planet under meager skies as
overcast by clouds that sky can be. Had
never served to veil my eyes so thickly,
nor covered them with such rough
textured stuff as smoke that wrapped us
there in purgatory. My eyes could not
endure remaining open so that my
faithful, knowledgeable escort drew
closer as he offered me his shoulder.
Just as a blind man moves behind his
guide, that he not stray or strike
against something that may do damage to
or even kill him. So I moved through the
bitter filthy air while listening to my
guide who kept repeating
not cut off from me. But I heard voices
and each seemed to pray unto the lamb of
God who takes away our sins for peace
and mercy. Agnus day was sung repeatedly
as their exordium. Words sung in such a
way in unison that fullest concord
seemed to be among them. Master, are
those whom I hear spirits? I asked him.
You have grasped rightly, he replied.
And as they go, they lose the knot of
anger. Then who are you whose body
pierces through our smoke, who speak of
as exactly like a man who uses months to
measure time? A voice said this, "Oh, on
hearing it, my master turned round to
me, replied to him, then ask if this way
leads us to the upward path, and I, oh
creature, who that you return fair unto
him who made you cleanse yourself, you
shall hear wonders if you follow me.
I'll follow you as far as I'm allowed,"
he answered. "And if smoke won't let us
see, hearing will surf instead to keep
us linked." Then I began with those same
swaddling bands that death unwinds I
take my upward path. I've come here by
way of health exactions. Since God so
gathered me into his grace that he would
have me in a manner most unusual for
modern see his court. Do not conceal
from me who you once were before your
death and tell me if I go straight to
the past your words will be our escort.
I was a Lumbard and I was called Marco.
I knew the world's ways and I loved
those good for which the bows of all men
now grow slack. The way you've taken
leads directly upward. So he replied and
then he added, I pray you to pray for me
when you're above and I to him I pledge
my faith to you to do what you have
asked. And yet a doubt will burst in me
if it finds no way out. Before my doubt
was simple, but your statement has
doubled it and made me sure that I'm
right to couple your word with anothers.
The world indeed has been stripped
utterly of every virtue. As you said to
me, it cloaks and is cloaked by
perversity. Some place the cause in
heaven some below. But I beseech you to
define the cause that seeing it I may
show it to others. Aside from which
sorrow formed, O was his beginning. Then
he answered, "Brother, the world is
blind, and you come from the world. You
living ones continue to assign to heaven
every cause as if it were the necessary
source of every motion. If this were so,
then your free will would be destroyed
and there would be no equity and joy for
doing good and grief for evil.
>> Okay. So, um Donnie meets a man named
Marco Lombard and they engage in a
debate of discussion. Okay. Has to do
with the nature of free will and we as
we explained earlier free will has to be
the fundamental law of the universe for
the universe to work properly. Okay. Uh
if you just think that God intervenes uh
and that a lot of things are
predetermined, [clears throat] um you're
not incentivized to do any good and
evil. Okay, you become fatalistic.
And uh so he says that free will has to
be the fundamental law of the universe.
Okay. Uh keep on going.
>> 73. The heavens set your appetites in
motion, not all your appetites. But even
if that were the case, you have received
both light on good and evil and free
will, which though it struggled in its
first wars with the heavens, then
conquers all, if it has been well
nurtured, on greater power, better
nature, you who are free, depend force
and genders the mind in you outside the
heavens way. Thus if the present world
has gone astray and you is the cause and
you it's to be sought and now I'll serve
as your true exedite issuing from his
hand the soul on which he thought with
love before creating it is like a child
who weeps and laughs in sport that soul
is simple unaware but since a joyful
maker gave it motion it turns willingly
to things that bring delight at first it
savors trivial goods these would beguile
the soul and it runs after them unless
there's guide or rain to rule its of
therefore one needed law to serve as
curb. A ruler too was needed. One who
would discern at least the tower of the
true city. The laws exist, but who
applies them now? No one, the shepherd,
who precedes his flock and chew the cut,
but does not have cleft hoops. And thus
the people who can see their guides
snatch only at that good for which they
feel some greed, would feed on that, and
seek no further. Miss Rule, you see, has
caused the world to be malevolent. The
cause is clearly not celestial forces.
They do not corrupt.
For Rome, who made the world good used
to have two sons, and they made visible
two paths, the world's path and the
pathway that is God's. Each has eclipsed
the other. Now the sword has joined the
shepherd's crook. The two together must
of necessity result in evil. Because so
joined, one need not feed the other,
fear the other. And if you doubt me,
watch the fruit and flower. For every
plant is known by what it sees. Within
the territory watered by Adij and Po,
one used to find valor and courtesy.
That is before Frederick was met by
strive. Now anyone ashamed of talking
with the right righteous or of meeting
them can journey there secure.
True. Three old men are there in whom
old times reprove the new and they find
God is slow and summoning them to a
better life. Curado de Palazzo Good
Guerado and Guido de Castell whom it is
better to call as do the French the
candid Lombard. You can conclude the
church of Rome confounds two powers in
itself into the filth. It falls and
fouls itself in its new burden. Good
Marco, I replied, you reason well and
now I understand why Levy's sons were
not allowed to share in legacies. But
what Gerardo is this whom you mention as
an example of the vanished people whose
present would reproach the savage age?
Either your speech deceives me or would
tempt me, he answered then, for you
whose speech is Tuscan seem to know
nothing of the good Gardo. There's no
other name by which I know him unless I
speak of him as Gaia's father. God be
with you. I come with you no father. You
see the rays that penetrate the smoke
already whitening. I must take leaf. the
angel has arrived before he sees me. So
he turned back and would not hear me
more.
>> Okay. So just to summarize the speech,
what he's doing is he's just um
explaining how the universe works as
we'll learn in paradise, right? So God
gave us free will. That is his greatest
gift to us. And what allows us to know
what's good, what's bad is we're always
seeking to return to him, right? We want
to turn towards him and that's what
brings us eternal delight. But because
we are young, we're immature, we don't
appreciate that. So we um get lost and
get confused and we seek material
pleasures. And in this chaos um a ruler
will come and try to organize us and
steer us towards God. Um but eventually
uh the ruler becomes corrupt himself.
And then what happens is God has sent
sent a divine messenger like Jesus or
Homer or Dante to remind us of who we
are to remind us that we are divine
sparks that seek to return to God. And
then from this person will arise a
religion, a church. And at first that's
good, but then what happens is that the
church and empire combine together and
then this causes a lot of corruption. Um
um but the main point is yes even though
this is just a natural course of history
um free will is the fundamental law of
the universe and therefore we must take
responsibility for our actions on earth.
We can't be like well the god god made
made us this way or whatever. No no god
gave us all free choice. Whatever we do
is because we choose to. So if we don't
like things the way they are we have to
go fix it. Okay. Yes. Um so the
fundamental rule of universe is free
will then how to um but you said before
there are good writers and bad writers
does that mean a kind of deterministic
um
>> no no writers are yes
>> I think that the way I would answer this
is just that bad writers are
not good at organizing the inspiration
they receive so they receive visions and
characters and stories But the way they
write it means that other beings have a
hard time putting their minds in the
story. So they just miscommunicate
whatever their inspiration is.
>> Okay. So so sorry. Um let let me explain
what I mean. Okay. What I mean are
writers who become historical figures,
writers who change the course of
history. People like Homer, Dante,
Shakespeare, Plato. Okay. These are
clearly divine prophets who are
compelled to be messengers for the monad
for the vine. Okay, what you're thinking
about is okay, is this guy a bestseller?
Is he technically proficient? That
doesn't matter. No one cares about these
people. Okay, you may care about these
people because they're alive today, but
100 years from now, no one's going to
read like like who's who's a famous
writer? Uh
uh it's me
>> JK. JK Rowling. No one's going to read
JK Rowling 100 years from now. Okay.
>> Um, so the prophets are determined
before uh by God.
>> Um, yeah. C can someone explain to him
how this works?
Uh,
uh, Anna, can you try? I
>> think good writers are willing to kind
of be a vessel for God's thing. So you
are very empty on the inside like yoga
right like when you're doing the posture
you empty yourself and then these things
come to you.
>> Uh so if you are bad yoga person then
you do all your postures and then you
make it look really good you balance
your yourself very well but then you are
not a channel so then you don't have
that divine connection to to write that
kind of works that changed the c course
of history.
>> Uh uh do did you want to say something?
Uh I think like I think those good
writers are just born with a different
filter, right? Cuz like you said, our
body is is basically a filter to feel to
feel the reality and they can choose to
they can be like either like wardrobe or
or dentist. They can choose like wardro
wardro to distort the the celestial
order to uh and raise the idiot, right?
or they can tr uh choose to be like
Dante to to uh convey this like uh
divine order to to the secular world.
Yeah.
>> Okay. Uh uh Bruce,
>> thank you. Uh I think uh there's so many
famous writers, some of writers in
America for example like uh uh
Hammingway, right? So all of these
writers just get through some kind of
painful very painful memory like in the
war, you know, in the war time. So some
some people they've been tortured so
much they really want to write
something. Okay. And even the Harry
Potter's writer JK Rowling who who just
been so poor in poor conditions in this
way imagination been so you know so much
better than others and he even keep
writing on the napkins about what to
write and Harry Potter is actually just
a jack's childhood. So
>> Fred did you want to say something?
No, I think other than I have to agree
with the filter point, but I just think
I really agree with that it's about
bad writers are people that let their
own mind and biases and experience cloud
the structure that would have would have
come into them.
>> Yeah. Like Virgil. Yes.
good or bad is also I think human
success can be defined by talent,
passion and perseverance or this filter.
So like some people are born like he
said like to be better writers because
the their filters are set in a way that
they are more likely to have this
invitation of divine uh revelation. But
then there were also other, you know,
>> do you guys read the New Yorker
magazine?
Just the most pretentious crap in this
world, okay? They spent decades
perfecting their crap. It's beautiful
word after word after word, signifying
nothing, full sound and theory. Okay?
That's what the New Yorker is. That's
what bad writing looks like. Okay.
All right. And so you're like, "Well,
but I mean like they're successful. No
one cares." Okay. All right. Let's
Sorry. Sorry. Sorry. I just hate New
Yorker. Let's Let's move on. Sorry.
[gasps]
>> Um, Kanto 17.
Remember, reader, if you've ever been
caught in the mountains by a mist
through which you only saw as moles see
through their skin, how when the thick
damp damp vapors once begin to thin, the
sun's sphere passes feebly through them.
Then your imagination will be quick to
reach the point where it can see how it
first came to see the sun again when it
was almost at that point at which it
sets. So my steps matched my master's
trusty steps. Out of that cloud I came,
reaching the rays that on the shores
below by now we're spent. Oh fantasy
that at times would snatch us so from
outward things we notice nothing.
Although a thousand trumpets sound
around us who moves you when the senses
do not spur you. A light that finds its
form and heaven moves you directly or
led downward by God's will. Within my
fantasy I saw impressed the savagery the
savagery of one who then transformed
became the bird that most delights in
song. At this my mind withdrew to the
within to what imagining might bring. No
thing that came from the without could
enter in.
>> Okay. So again he's having visions now.
Okay. These visions just come to him.
There's nothing he can do about it.
These are just visions that are sent
down to him. Um okay. So so let's look
at the visions.
Then into my deep fantasy there reigned
one who was crucified and as he died he
showed his savagery and disdain. Line 28
around him were great aes and Esther his
wife and the just Morsedai Moriceai
whose sang and whose doing were so
upright. And when this image shattered
of itself just like a bubble that has
lost the water beneath which it was
formed, there then rose up in my
envisioning a girl who wept most
bitterly and said, "Oh queen, why did
you in your wrath desire to be no more
so as to keep Levvenia? You killed
yourself. Now you have lost me. I am
she, mother, who mourns your fall before
anothers. Even asleep is shattered when
new light strikes suddenly against
closed eyes. And once it's shattered,
gleams before it dies completely. So my
imagination fell away as soon as light
more powerful than light we're
accustomed to beat on my eyes. I looked
about to see where I might be. But when
a voice said, "Hear one can ascend."
Then I abandoned every other intent.
That voice made my will my will keen to
see the one who' spoken with the
eagerness that cannot be still until it
faces what it wants. But even as the sun
becomes so strong, defeats art vision,
veiling its own form, so there my power
of sight was overcome. This spirit is
divine and though unass he would conduct
us to the upward path. He hides himself
with that same light he sheds. He does
this he does with us as men do with
themselves. For he who sees a need but
waits to be asked is already set on
cruel refusal. Now let our steps accept
his invitation and let us try to climb
before dark falls. Then until day
returns we'll have to halt.
So sat my guide and toward a stairway he
and I together turned and just as soon
as I was at the first step I sense
something much like the motion of a wing
and wind that beat against my face and
words
pivichi those free of evil anger above
us now the final rays before the fall of
night were raised to such a height that
we could see the stars on every side. Oh
why my strength do you so melt away? I
said within myself because I felt the
force within my legs compelled to halt.
We'd reach a point at which the upward
stairs no longer climbed and we were
halted there just like a ship when it
was touched the shore. It has touched
the shore.
I listened for a while hoping to hear
whatever there might be in this new
circle. Then I turned toward my master
asking him tell me my gentle father what
offense is perched within the cycle
circle we have reached. Although our
feet must stop, your words need not. And
he to me precisely here the love of good
that is too tepidly pursued is mended.
Here the lazy ore plies harder. And so
that you may understand more clearly.
Now turn your mind to me and you will
gather some useful fruit from our
delaying here. My son, there's no
creator and no creature whoever was
without love, natural or mental. And you
know that he began the natural is always
without error but mental love may choose
an evil object or earth through too much
or too little vigor
as long as it's directed toward the
first good and tends towards secondary
goods with measure it cannot be the
cause of evil pleasure but when it
twists toward evil or tends to good with
more or less care than it should. Those
whom he made have worked against their
maker. From this you see that of
necessity, love is the seed in you of
every virtue virtue and of all acts
deserving punishment. Now since love
never turns aside its eyes from the
well-being of its subject, things are
surely free of hatred of themselves. And
since no being can be seen as
self-existing and divorced from the
first being, each creature is cut off
from hating him. Thus, if I have
distinguished properly, ill love must
mean to wish one's neighbor ill. And
this love's born in three ways in your
clay. There's he who through a basement
of another hopes for supremacy. He only
longs to see his neighbors excellence
cast down. Then there's one who when
he's outdone fears his own loss of fame,
power, honor, favor. His sadness loves
misfortune for his neighbor. And there's
he who over injury received, resentful
for revenge, grows greedy and angrily
seeks out another's harm. This
three-fold love is expedated here below.
Now I would have you understand the love
that seeks the good distortedly. Each
apprehends confusedly a good in which
the mind may rest and longs for it. And
thus all strive to reach that good. But
if the love that urges you to know it or
to reach that good is lacks, this
terrorist after a just repentance
punishes for that. There's a different
good which does not make men glad. It is
not happiness. It's not true as since
fruit and root of every good. The love
that profle proflegatly yields to that
is wept on in three terraces above us.
But I'll not say what three shape that
love takes. May you seek those
distinctions for yourself.
>> Okay. So um just like in hell uh Virgil
is explain explaining to us how um
purgatory is structured. He's saying
that that the last three terraces are
the three um um terraces of gluttony,
lust, and greed. Okay, greed, gluttony,
and lust are the last on the top three.
And the reason why they're they're on
the top three is they are love that is
misguided. Okay, uh greed is a love of
power, right? When you should be
actually loving God. Uh gluttony is a
love of food. And then lust is just um
spirious love, random love. Okay. So it
is love that is misguided. Um and they
are the ones which um confuse you. Okay.
All right. Uh let's go on to 18. Okay.
[clears throat]
Kanto 18.
The subtle teacher had completed his
discourse to me. Attentively he watched
my eyes to see if I seemed satisfied.
And I still goated by new thirst was
silent without although within I said
perhaps I have displeased him of too
many questions. But that true father who
had recognized the timid want I would
not tell aloud by speaking gave me
courage to speak out at which I said
master my sight is so illumined by your
light. I recognize all that your words
declare or analyze. Therefore I pray you
gentle father dear to teach me what love
is. You have reduced to love both each
good and its opposite.
>> Okay. All right. So this is actually a
really important cat. Okay. And I want
us to focus on this viral now is going
to explain to us what love is. Why is it
love can go astray? Okay. What is good
love? What is bad love? Okay.
All right. So, uh let us listen to his
explanation.
>> Line line 16. He said, "Direct your int
direct your intellects sharp eyes toward
me and let the air of the blind serve as
guides be evident to you. The soul which
is created quick to love responds to
everything that pleases just as soon as
beauty wakens it to act. Your
apprehension draws an image from a real
object and and expands upon that object
until soul has turned toward it. And if
so turned the soul tends steadfastly,
then that propensity is love. Its nature
that joins the soul in you a new through
beauty. Then just as flames ascend
because the form of fire was fashioned
to fly upward toward the stuff of its
own sphere where it lasts longest so
does the soul when seeds moved into
longing emotion of the spirit never
resting till the beloved thing has made
it joyous. Now you can plainly see how
deeply hidden truth is from scrutinists
who would insist that every love is in
itself praiseworthy and they're led to
error by the matter of love because it
may seem always good but not each seal
is fine although the wax is. Your speech
and my own wit that followed it I
answered him have shown me what love is
but that has filled me with still
greater doubt. For if love's offered to
us from without and is the only foot
with which soul walks, soul going
straight or crooked has no merit. And he
to me what reason can see here I can
impart. Past that for truth of faith its
beatress alone you must await. Every
substantial form at once distinct from
matter and conjoined to it and gathers
the force that is distinctly
distinctively its own. A force unknown
to us until it acts. It's never shown
except in its effects just as green
boughs display the life in plants. And
thus man does not know the source of his
intelligence of primal notion and his
tending toward desires primal objects.
Both are a new just as in bees. There is
the honeymaking urge. Such primal will
deserves no praise and it deserves no
blame. Now that all other longings may
conform to this first will, there's in
you inborn the power that counsels,
keeper of the threshold of your ascent.
This is the principle on which your
merit may be judged, for it garers and
winners good and evil belongings. Those
reasoners who reach the roots of things
learned of its inborn freedom. The
bequest that thus they left unto the
world is ethics. Even if we allow
necessity as source for every love that
flames in you, the power to curb that
love is still your own. This noble power
is what Beatrice means by free will.
Therefore, remember it if she should
ever speak of it to you.
>> Okay? So again, this is a very important
speech. Okay? And this is really the
fighting speech um the dividing uh
dialogue between Dante and Virgil.
Remember how we said that uh at the end
of Infernal, Virgil gave birth to Dante
and throughout this process, it was
Virgil that was guiding Dante. Well, at
this point, uh this dialogue, this
debate is going to mark
um when Dante and Virgil have their
separation. Okay.
So, let's figure out why Dante and
Virgil, they must separate.
So [clears throat]
Virgil's saying this, you're walking the
streets and
sitting
uh in the restaurant outside in a
terrorist is the most beautiful woman
you've ever seen. If if you're a woman,
you're ob obviously the most handsome
guy you've seen. Okay. All right. But
but but just for the sake of argument,
let's let's use beautiful woman. Okay.
For the sake of some simplicity. Um,
and what do you want to what do you want
to do now?
Come on.
>> Ask her.
>> Yeah. You you you want to go say hi.
Like, hey, how are you? You sit down
beside her. Okay. [snorts] And um, what
what happens next?
Okay.
What happens next? You're talking to
her. You're like, "Hey, how are you?
What a beautiful day."
Um, if you're a Virgil, what do you
aspire to do?
>> Possessor.
>> Yeah. It's you want to possess her,
right? If you actually read his speech,
he's talking about how what love is, it
is your soul expanding outwards to
possess another soul of beauty. Okay?
You your soul wants to encompass, okay?
Literally dominate, control another
person. Okay? And what? So, and so if
Virgil wants to possess her, how is
Donnie different? What does Donnie want
to do?
>> Well, what should you do before you
praise her?
Come on, guys. Have you ever dated? Yes.
Yes. Brad,
>> learn about her.
>> Yeah. Get to know her, guys. Okay. Not
hard. Ask her, "Hey, where you from?
What do you like to do?" Okay.
Right. So what Virgil is saying is
that's what love is. Love is basically
lust. You see someone beautiful and you
want to have her. Okay.
And so what happens if she says you're
ugly or I don't like you.
What would Virgil do?
>> Yes.
>> Put Put her in hell.
>> Well, yeah, that's what he does
ultimately. But what but but what does
he do beforehand?
>> [snorts and clears throat]
>> um he'll get mad and then he'll make
like negative comments on like, "Oh,
you're not that good either." Whatever.
But
>> but what what do you do? What What do
you do that makes you mad at her?
>> Cuz she's not praising you back.
>> What would Virgil do? Okay. Like like
you know, they have they have lunch and
then Virgil's like, "Wow, you're so
beautiful." And then she's like, you
know, I'm not that interested in you.
What would Virgil do? Come on. Yes.
>> Well, he would say like try to introduce
a contract of duty between the two. So
he said, "I love you so much that you
should not do that." Yes.
>> He'll write a poem like the In I forgot
how to pronounce that.
>> Iniad, something like that. Cuz I think
that girl also kind of refused to talk
to him, I think. Okay. Okay. Like, no.
Seriously, come on. Come. This is not
hard. Okay. Have you guys not dated?
Okay. Yes.
>> He He'll ask why.
>> No, he won't.
He won't care. What will he do?
>> You mean No, he won't.
>> Maybe insult her or something.
>> Come on.
>> Maybe he would just walk away.
>> No.
Jimmy, how how do you insist? He will
try to reason her out and persuade her.
>> Oh, guys, come on.
How about buy her flowers? How about buy
her chocolates? How about buy her a
diamond ring? How about buy her a
Mercedes? How about like take her to
Monaco for the Grand Prix? How about
like, you know, induce her to like
Jackie Chan? How about How about buy her
a villa, right? How about um take her to
the moon? Like you know,
right? He won't stop.
And then if he gets rejected, what will
he do?
He'll put her in hell, man. He'll write
the internet and put her in hell. You
understand? That's what literally he
will do,
right? For like years and years, he will
pursue you and you'll be like, "No." And
he'll try harder and harder. Okay,
that's that's Virgil's conception of
love.
Tell tell me how Donnie is different.
Yes, Edward. Did Did you Did you want to
>> try? Um, if he was rejected, he would
just continue to love her.
>> Would he get rejected? Um, Anna,
>> just getting to know her and praise her
and then write poetry for her. And if
she rejects him, usually she wouldn't, I
guess, because he's so loving. But if
she does, then he will continue to love
her regardless of her reaction to him.
But I love you because I love you. I
don't need you to love me back because
the true essence of love is let just
love. Like you just flow. And like if
you don't love me, that's fine.
>> Yeah. Yes.
Sorry. So, what is your name?
>> I'm Crystal. And I was trying to make a
similar point. So,
>> Okay. Thanks, Chris. Okay. All right.
What does Virgil want at the end of the
day when he's sending her flowers and
buying her a diamond ring? What What's
he really want?
>> Sex.
>> Yeah. He all he wants is sex, man. Okay.
That for him, that's what love is. Okay.
Sex. Does Johnny want sex?
>> Yes.
>> Part of it. No, he does not. Okay, guys.
Guys. Yes.
>> I think the answer to the first part,
like how he would um seduce her, he
basically try and get to know her as
long as it took that it was impossible
for her to deny that there was another
soul present in her presence. Um, but I
think that he doesn't want sex because I
think it was his love for Beatrice who
he couldn't like who he never really had
sex with that was like he was thinking
how can I love this person so much but
I'm not trying to procreate or I'm
blocked from procreating because she
died young.
>> Right. Also, um, historically this this
is the time of the courty love
tradition. Courty love tradition. So
you're supposed to like just worship a
woman but not possess her. Okay. from
you're supposed to worship her from
afar. Usually it's a married woman.
Usually it's someone someone you can
never ever um have, but you just write
poetry in praise of her. Something
called a courty love tradition. The tr
the tropodors or the provincials in
France. And so Delo who we met
previously was part of this troubador
tradition. Okay. So um Dante he would
not be interested in in the sex. he
would think that love is the uh perfect
expression of his devotion, of his
faith, of his individuality. Okay, does
that make sense? Okay, so these are two
ext
the center of the whole comedy and
that's the Kanto that focuses on free
will. And now we get this we don't we
get a lecture on love which doesn't seem
symmetrical from paradise or inferno.
And so it's like the free will kind of
has led into this concept of love the
center of the the whole comedy.
>> Right. Okay. So you're absolutely right.
This is actually the very center of the
vivine comedy and this is where Dawn and
Virgil Okay. It's almost like this is
the final battle between the two. Okay.
where heaven and hell meet and don
obviously represents heaven and Virgil
represents hell. This is world the
cosmos and they're going to discuss what
love is. Okay, so you're absolutely
right. This is crucial structurally and
they discuss what love is and we've
already distinguished that Virgil sees
love as the expression of your uh ego
and you you want to dominate the other
person. you want to possess the other
person. Whereas for Dante, love is about
giving. Okay? And and this is very clear
when we we reach paradise. Okay? So this
is where he he h heaven and hell meet,
right? This is the final battle between
the between the two. And this is where
they will ultimately separate and go
their separate ways. Um
how does Virgil define free will here?
What is free will?
[snorts]
You see this beautiful woman,
you talk to her, you buy her flowers,
you buy her diamond ring, you give her
like money, and all you want to is is
have sex with her. What is free will in
Virgil's understanding of things?
That you're free to do whatever you
want. So, it doesn't really matter what
she wants or what she wants to do that
you have the freedom to pursue her as
much as you like and follow what you
want as much as you.
>> What is good and evil here? Uh Francois,
>> well for Virgil is having what he wants
and for Dante is wanting what he wants.
C
>> can you explain what the difference?
>> So for example like Virgil because he
wants something free will be having it.
Uh even though like a lot of things make
it impossible whereas Dante it's just I
think of it and even though it doesn't
reach that point just the fact of I'm
free to think and free to imagine having
it.
>> Okay. Yeah. That that that's that that
that's right. Yes. Okay. Does someone
want to expand on that?
Uh Edward, did you did you want to say
something?
Okay. For for Virgil, what is good and
evil then?
For for Virgil, what is good and evil?
>> Yes. Uh no J
um
>> uh good and evil. I I really like
Branch's comment on uh having versus
wanting. I think that's that is
mindblow. Uh it's it really leads uh
guides my imagination. I think for for
Virgil is having uh evil is having the
wrong things, good is having the right
things. For Dante uh good is wanting the
right things and evil is wanting the
wrong things.
>> Right. Yes. Okay.
>> Okay. Uh Anna,
>> I feel like for Virgil, like what's good
is confirming to his will.
Uh and what's bad is what's refusing his
ego's manifestation. So if the woman
refuses him, then she he condemns her to
hell ultimately. So it's not about
whether the women's choice was right or
wrong, but the fact that she rejected
him.
>> No. No. That's not that that's not how
how Virgil will proceed. Okay? Because
remember we have to think that Virgil is
a real person with real ideas. Okay, you
just say it to yourself. That doesn't
really make sense. Okay, for Virgil,
what is good and evil is
um love and this is really important.
Okay, love is neither good or evil.
If love takes you to a good place and
you allow good to take you that that
place, that's good. But if love takes
you into an evil place, you have to
reject love. Then that's what's good.
You understand? That's what free will
is. Free will is
to deny yourself when you know the thing
is wrong. Okay.
How does this conflict with Virgil then?
Oh, sorry. How does this conflict with
Dante? Because Virgil says love is
neutral. Love can be good or bad. Free
will is to know the difference and to
act accordingly. Right?
What would Donnie say?
Come on. We we we read paradise. We we
know what what Donnie says. Yes. It's
like follow your heart.
>> Good can never be evil. Sorry. Love can
never be evil. Love is always good.
Okay.
Then then then then then how to explain
when you see this beautiful woman and
like you love her so much you want to
give your life to her.
How how how to explain this?
>> Dante doesn't call misguided love.
>> It's not love. It's lust. You
understand? If you see this woman, you
want to have sex with her. That's not
love. That's lust. Okay. Love is giving
yourself. Love is hoping the best for
her, right? It's like, "How can I help
you? How can I be your friend? How can I
support you?" That's what love is. It's
not like I want to have sex with you.
That's just what lust is. Okay? And
Virgil does not know the difference.
Whereas Donnie does know the difference.
That's why Dante's stuck in limbo and
why Virgil stuck in in limbo and D's
going to heaven. That's the difference.
This is where they separate. Okay.
All right. Okay. Is that clear, guys?
Uh, yes.
>> I still don't understand why this
argument is even happening when when
when Virgil knows the truth, right? He
knows the truth about everything because
he's a prophet, so a poet or prophet. So
why why are they arguing when when when
Virgil should know the truth and he
doesn't have any obstacle to not speak
the truth about love that he should know
to Dante. Okay. So again this goes back
to the idea of absolute will and
contingent will. Okay. Absolute will is
what your soul is. Okay. Contingent will
is what you choose to do. So Virgil
knows the absolute truth of the universe
but he's made certain choices that has
clouded his understanding of things.
Okay. So he is a poet. He knows the
complete truth of the universe but he
chose to write the iniad to serve empire
and so that's going to cloud his
understanding of the way things work.
Right? Once you make an action you have
to justify this action. Does that make
sense? Right? Once you make this action
you have to be like this is a red
action. You can't be like, "Oh, it's it
was it was a mistake." So once you make
this action and you now have to go
justify it by changing your worldview.
Okay? So even though he knows the
absolute truth, he needs to make certain
adjustments to this theory in order to
make his actions make sense to him,
right? So he knows that love is giving
yourself. But then like why did you
write this the poem the Iniad and why
did you let I guess let you censor it
and you know better, right? And you're
like, well, okay, it's and so what what
you do is rather than just say I'm
wrong, you change your worldview. Does
that make sense?
Okay.
>> So, he's he's weighed down by his past
actions that he can't he's not able to
change himself.
>> And that's what sin is, right?
>> Sin is you are weighed down by your
actions and you refuse to forgive
yourself. And so, you just you just you
just you just basically uh put yourself
in hell for all of eternity. Okay,
doesn't make sense. Vers problem is he
refuses to admit he's wrong. He would
rather forget. He would rather just burn
in hell than to admit, you know what? I
was wrong to write the ad. Okay. All
right, guys. So, so we'll take a break.
We'll come back uh at lunch after lunch.
Okay. Uh welcome back. Good afternoon.
So to start we have a special pres
presentation from Francois and um he's
going to talk about how he perceives um
how memory works. Okay. So um uh
Francois.
>> Yeah. Uh hello everyone. So I was just
like looking at Jang's work and how he
represent represented things and uh it
was really messy and uh it seems like
you were channeling the wrong guy I feel
like.
>> Right.
>> Uh so yeah basically did this this map
on the right. So this was like our
discussion before about psychology. Uh
so it is still like quite vague but you
understand the most of it. And on the
right so um there's a big like circle
where there's a source in the middle
which is the monad. So like energy and
all and so it sparks like it's very v
vibrant from the middle and then it
extends into some very flat um circle.
And so how I look at it is that on the
exterior it's more about uh present
material and ego. And so if your
consciousness is directed like in this
realm then you'll think about like
money, time, house, material objects
about yourself etc. And like depending
on situations and moments in your life
then your consciousness is more directed
in the center where you like think more
of low love, hope and family and like
etc. It's just like um a whole idea and
uh also I saw something
of like who is it Rubert Sheldrake?
>> Yes. Yes. He is a physicist. Yes. Can
you explain his theory?
>> So basically I saw something about
morphic resonance where there is some
patterns and if people start thinking in
a way I think there's like a pattern and
people like diverge into this kind of
consciousness. So I feel like and so I
feel like in today's world there is like
incuring a converging point into like
the exterior realm
media polics and AI where our
consciousness is directed into thinking
about uh money time fear etc. Whereas I
see the divine comedy as more directing
us into the center of this uh
consciousness.
And so just like a point I made like
think of this. I feel like angels are
more meant to push us inward and demons
outward in a way. And I think it's
really movable. So depending on the
moment in your life and uh during the
day your consciousness just like moves
around there.
>> Yeah. Okay. Great. So um a few points.
First of all um this is great by the
way. This is fantastic. Um but my first
point is remember yesterday professor
Brahmer told us that uh William James uh
he believed goals actually exist but
they were really boring. Okay they not
actually have much consciousness and
this is something that we experience in
divine harmony as well where there are
angels and demons but they don't really
do anything. Okay but the thing is like
they're all around us and and this is
what what what the theory is like like
we're surrounded always by these angels
and demons who are torn in different
directions. Okay, that's the first part.
Second point is that Rudolph Selj is
really interesting. So if you have a
chance, please watch his interviews, his
presentations um online. But but to show
but to prove a point I I'll do an
experiment. Okay. So first of all, can
you can you face the uh screen? Okay.
You're going to face the screen. Okay.
And then and then I'm going to have um
Edward come and what Yes. No. No. No.
No. Send behind him. Send behind him.
Okay. Okay. And send behind him. All
right. So, I want you to turn away from
him. Okay. All right. So, we're going to
see Okay. We'll do an experiment, okay?
Where Edward's going to turn around and
look at uh Francois. Okay. And Fran,
could you please close your eyes? Okay.
Okay. So, obviously, if Francois turns
around
um before Edward turns around, then
Francois loses against this game. Okay.
Right. So, we're trying to figure out
how long it will take for uh everyone's
going to turn around. Okay. And when
everyone turns around, I I want to I
want us to count how long it takes for
Francois to turn around. Okay? And
remember, if France turns around first
and he obviously loses, okay? Does that
does it make sense, guys? This is just
an experiment, okay? It's not a test. Um
but uh let's start. Okay. On three. And
again, it's entirely Edward's choice.
We're going to turn around. He could
choose not to turn around if if he wants
to. I mean, he we could be here for
another two hours. Okay. But but but
we're we're going to count how long it
takes silently for France to turn around
when Edward turns around. Okay. All
right. So, let's start. 1 2 3 go.
Wow. You guys see that? That was pretty
fast, man. Thank you. Thank you both.
Okay. You see that? You guys saw that?
So, Francois, how do you how do you how
did you know?
C can you can you big like we waited a
long time. I was getting impatient. I
was like, "What's going on here, man?"
>> Just through like So, I was focusing on
my respiration and I felt there was a
moment I was like in control of the
situation. I felt it was the right
moment.
>> Okay.
That was pretty that was pretty fast,
right? I I was I was impressed because
like I think it was like less than 2
seconds like like how long was it?
Yeah. And like Edward was being sneaky
about it too, right? He was like, I'm
going to trick him and like were you
surprised,
right? So, this is actually what Rubert
Cedric does. He does this sort of
research and he's trying to figure out
how this happens
like like how how does this happen,
right? If you use standard neuroscience,
it gets you nowhere, right? Uh but um if
you believe though that
we actually exist in different
dimensions and we have uh morphic
fields. Okay. So so basically we project
outwards
and so this sort of stuff is possible
but also you think about it telepathy
telekinesis is also possible to a
certain degree. Okay. Um and this is
something we'll we'll discuss as we
continue divine comedy. Now where our
souls are, our souls are essentially
these morphic fields. Okay. And so when
Edward is turning around and staring at
friends, our friends are turning around
because there's a connection at the soul
level. Okay. And that's why the reaction
is so fast.
Weird, right? Okay. Well, there you go.
All right. Let's continue the vine
comedy.
Have you guys not seen this before?
Yeah.
Again, like the point is there's so much
interesting stuff out there, but we
close our minds to it, right? We we have
these prejudices about how the world
works, and so we shut up our minds to
these possibilities.
What's your impression of that?
I knew that.
>> But like but like when we saw it happen,
weren't you kind of like shocked?
>> Yeah, it was kind of shocking, right?
Because like I knew it happened, too,
but like I didn't know it would happen
that instantly, right? That fast. Were
you surprised?
>> Yeah.
>> As I always said,
>> also you put us all in tune.
>> Yes.
>> You put us all in tune. We've been doing
this for 10 11 days.
>> Yes. Yes. [clears throat]
Yes. [laughter]
Uh, excuse me.
>> No, just Yeah, I waited a long time. Uh,
>> yeah, you did. I was getting
I was like, why man?
>> So, I'd waited so long. So, I thought
when I finally turned around, you know,
it might take him a while then to turn
around.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> And then he basically as soon as I
turned around, looked at him, he turned
around.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It happens pretty fast.
Okay. All right, guys. Let's let's let's
continue Divine Comedy. Okay.
Um, Kanto 18, line 76.
The moon with midnight now behind us
made the star seem scarer to us, scarcer
to us. It was shaped just like a copper
basin, gleaming new and countercourse.
It crossed those paths the sun ignites
when those in Rome can see it set
between the Corsicans and the
Sardinians. That gracious shade for whom
Pollola, one more renowned than any
Manchu in town, had freed me from the
weight of doubt I bore, so that I,
having harvested his clear and open
answers to my question, stood like one
who, nearing sleep, has random visions.
But readiness for sleep was suddenly
taken from me by people who behind our
bags backs already turned in our
direction. Just as of old isminus and
esopus at night along their banks saw
crowds and clamor whenever theans had to
summon bakas. Such was the arching crowd
that curved around that circle driven on
as I made out by righteous will as well
as by just love. Soon all that mighty
throng drew near us, for they ran and
ran, and two in front of them who wept
were crying. In her journey, Mary made
haste to reach the mountain, and in
order to conquer Larida, for Caesar
thrust against Moxay, and then to Spain,
he rushed. Following them, the others
cried, "Quick, quick, lest time be lost
through an insufficient love. Where
urged for good is keen, grace finds new
green. Oh people in whom eager fervor
now may compensate for sloth and
negligence he showed in doing good
half-heartedly.
He whose alive and surely I don't lie to
you would climb above as soon as he has
seen the sunshed light on us again. Then
tell us where the passage lies at hand.
My guide said this. One of the souls
replied, "Come follow us and you will
find the gap. We're so fully anxious to
advance, we cannot halt. And do forgive
us should you take our penance for
discourtesy. I was St. Zenos Abbott and
Verona under the rule of valiant
Barbarasa of whom Alain still speaks
with so much sorrow and there's one with
one foot in the grave who soon will weep
over that monastery lamenting that he
once had power there because in place of
its true shepherd he put one who was
unsound of body and still more of mind
and born in sin his son I don't know if
he had said more or was silent he had
already raised so bar far beyond us but
I heard heard this much and was pleased
to hear it. And he who was my help in
every need said, "Turn around. See those
two coming? They whose words mock
sloth." And I heard those two say behind
all of the rest. The ones for whom the
sea parted were dead before the Jordan
saw those who had inherited its lands.
And those who did not suffer trials
until the end together with Anaciz's son
gave themselves up to life without
renown. Then when those shades were so
far off from us that seeing them became
impossible, a new thought rose inside me
and from that from that thought till
others many and diverse were born. I was
so drawn from random thought to thought
that wandering in mind I shut my eyes
transforming thought on thought to
dream.
>> So a new thought rose inside of me and
it kept on going. Okay. So that's what
happens as you become much more
virtuous. you become much more connected
to the divine consciousness and more and
more uh visions are downloaded into you.
Okay, that's a process at work. All
right, let's keep on going.
KTO 19.
In that hour when the heat of day
defeated by earth and sometimes Saturn
can no longer warm up the moon sent
cold. When geommancers can in the east
see their fortuna major rising before
the dawn along a path that will be
darkened for it only briefly. A
stammering woman came to me in dream.
Her eyes skew and crooked on her feet.
Her hands were crippled. Her complexion
salow. I looked at her and just as sun
revives cold limbs that night made numb.
So did my gaze loosen her tongue, and
then in little time set her contorted
limbs in perfect order, and with the
coloring that love prefers, my eyes
transformed the wness of her features.
And when her speech had set free, then
she began to sing so that it would have
been most difficult for me to turn
aside. I am, she sang, I am the pleasing
siren who in midse mariners astray.
There's so much delight in hearing me. I
turned aside Ulyses, although he had
longed to journey, who gross youth to me
seldom departs, I satisfy him so. Her
lips were not yet done, when there
beside me a woman showed herself, alert
and saintly, to cast the siren into much
confusion. Oh, Virgil, Virgil, tell me,
who is this? She asked most scornfully,
and he came forward, his eyes intent
upon that honest one. He sees the other
bearing her in front, tearing her
clothes and showing me her belly. The
stench that came from there awakened me.
I moved my eyes and my good master
cried, "At least three times I've called
you. Rise and come. Let's find the
opening where you may enter."
>> Okay. All right. So, this is another
dream. Okay. So, again, as Virgil is
kind of up higher, more and more visions
come to him. And this is a very strange
dream, right? Because Donnie is being
seduced by the siren, right? Right. The
sign who seduced Ulisses.
And then a woman barges in and shouts,
"Oh, Virgil, Virgil, tell me who is
this?"
And then Virgil comes forward and then
he seizes the siren
um and tears her clothes apart.
What What's going on here? Okay,
let's try to figure out what this dream
is about. Remember the last dream that
um Donna had was a vision from heaven uh
where say Lucia uh as an eagle picks him
up and delivers him to the gates of
purgatory.
What is going on here? And again again I
don't know the answer. It's all
interpretation, right? It's all
speculation. So can someone tell me what
is going on here? What is this dream
about
[snorts]
in our understanding of the divine
comedy? Who is the siren?
Do you mean?
Uh, okay. Yeah, I I know the siren is a
woman, but I'm saying like so far in our
story, who should be the who should be
the siren? Yeah, it's Virgil, right?
Okay. So, if we think if we see this, we
think it's maybe it's Virgil because
Virgil is the one seducing Donnie
throughout, right? Uh with his poetry.
Uh and throughout all this time, Dante
has been a student, a child of Virgil's,
right? So, it seems as though it sounds
like Virgil is the one seducing Dante
and leading him astray,
but then
something weird happens.
Beatrice comes in. I think it's Beatric,
you know, maybe it's Beatric. She's
like, "Virgil, Virgil, tell me who is
this?
Where's Dante here?"
Yes.
when Virgil comes forward, he's behind
Dante. So, um, because he's barring her
in front, it's almost like he's hiding
herself. And I think that when he's
showing Dante her belly, it's a message
from Beatric saying like, you are,
please don't get still born in Virgil
such that you would start to rot as a
baby.
um that the siren is like a love that
has been left to fester and that's why
it wake that's why it smells.
>> Okay, that's really interesting. Okay,
but first answering this question
um
what should Beatric be really saying?
What should what should Beatric be
saying
to me?
No, no. So, so it seems as though Don is
being seduced, right? Beatress comes in
and what she should be saying rather
than, "Oh, Virgil, Virgil, tell me who
is this
>> and be like, she'll probably be like,
>> she is pissed right now when she asked
scornfully."
>> Yeah.
>> But what is strange or paradoxical about
what she's saying?
Because Virgil should be the siren. But
now there's another siren.
>> Yeah. Why sound to Virgil? She should be
talking to Dante, right? It's Donn's
dream. Beatric is Donnie's beloved,
right? This is a dream. D So, so
visualize this. Dante is staring at a
siren. He's being seduced by the siren.
C.
>> Can you explain?
So, in this dream, Dante is Virgil.
>> Yeah. And and and why is this a problem?
>> What does this tell tell Dante?
>> It's a Clarion call that he's gone too
far
in his bond with Virgil.
>> Okay. Yes. Anyone else? Yes. I think in
the moment when you have to kill your
father as a man or or whatever the case
may be. Um that final moment is when you
realize your greatest affinity with the
father. So you're thinking these are the
things that make me like him. This is
how I am him
>> and and you use him as a final
projection. You say all right I'm him
now I'm gonna it's over.
>> Yeah. Have you guys watched Star Wars?
>> Right. You you I I know you watch Star
Wars,
>> but you remember the scene where um is
it is it episode 2? Um but but you know
like
>> like Luke has to kill his father, right?
So he kills someone, he discovers it's
his father.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. When it opens it, it's it's like
himself, right?
>> Okay. So it's playing to that idea. It
doesn't make sense, guys. Okay. So, so
that conversation that that dialogue
between Dante and Virgil, it's a turning
point now because it sounds correct, but
there's a part to it that Dante knows
it's not correct. Okay? And now his
connection to the divine is giving him
images to show him it's not correct. In
fact, the universe is now warning him,
be aware of Virgil. You are now Virgil.
Right?
Okay.
Does that make sense, guys? Yes.
>> It's especially because after it's right
after um Virgil delivered his speech
about love and so Dante's almost like
inhibiting his worldview
to his right. So he's like becoming
Virgil in that aspect and especially
like understanding love is like the most
important thing for Dante that he gets
it right.
>> Yes. Exactly. Yes. Thank you. Okay. All
right. [snorts]
But but you see how like once you
connect the vine, the vine will steer
you in the right direction. Do you do
you understand? Like what's important is
to connect yourself to the vine through
love. Once once that happens, the vine
will give you messages to show you the
way even though you you may yourself may
be corrupted. All right, let's keep on
going. Does anyone else want to add
something to the stream? Because again,
this is a very complex stream. Okay, I
don't I don't want to oversimplify it.
Yes. Um, I think it's quite telling that
Betus Betrice asked Virgil to identify
the siren because it's kind of the love
that we were talking about that Virgil
has that turns
>> uh the ugly lady into a beautiful one.
That
>> the idea that he could possess her makes
her beautiful when in fact it's she's
like salow and and ugly and malformed.
>> Um, yeah. Anna
>> yeah it also makes me think about this
whole idea in the Greek tradition that
the first two or three gods like before
Zeus they were all father killing so
this idea of almost epitus theory like
you have to kill your father to become
yourself it's also the turning point
like past 16 right like halfway through
uh purgatory that now your first half of
your life is childhood you're imitating
your dad and you know you want to be him
or you battle him a little bit in
teenage you know when you're teen
teenager and then finally I guess maybe
this is the turning point in which he
becomes adulthood which is killing of
one's father.
>> Okay. Um the other thing I will point
out is like how the universe talks to
you is through images that evoke
emotions. Do you understand? Right. The
images don't really mean that much. The
images are meant to convey emotion to to
like provoke an emotion in you that lead
you to the correct path.
So,
um I mean what I think my interpretation
is this, okay? Uh
if I'm Dante,
I see this dream and I'm extremely
uncomfortable. I'm extremely
uh anxious. And the reason why is
I feel as though Beatatrice and Virgil
might become one with each other. Does
that make sense? Because it's Virgil who
goes and does Beatus bidding. Okay. So,
so it's one of like
Virgil is my competitor now. You
understand? That's the emotion now.
Before it's like Virgil's my father. Now
he's like no, no, no, no. Virgil is my
competitor. I I need to watch out. I
mean like if I really want to keep
Beatric, I need to show I am more worthy
than Virgil that I am more willing to do
sacrifice myself for Beatatric.
>> Yeah. Which in a way is very adep
complex too, right? Leoian concept is
that the first few years of your life
the little boy wants to imitate the
father and after that he's like, "Oh,
he's a competitor to my mom, you know,
for me, so I have to kill him." So it's
>> Right. Okay. But you see how how with
Dante just a few lines are so rich,
right? They're so pregnant. You can go
on and on and try to analyze what's
going on, but there's so many different
layers, right? Okay. So, I think, you
know, again, the what's causing this
dream is Virgil's exposition of love,
right? And Don Hart knows, no, no, no,
this is this doesn't make any sense, but
he doesn't know why it doesn't make any
sense because he's not mature enough,
right? So the universe gives him these
dreams that reveal to him Virgil is your
competitor. Okay. Be wary of what he
just said.
Okay. Does it make sense, guys? Okay.
All right. Let's keep on going.
>> 37.
I rose. The daylight had already filled
the circles of the sacred mountain. We
were journeying with new sun at our
back. I followed him, bearing my brow
like one whose thoughts have weighed him
down, who bends as if he were this
semiarchch that forms a bridge. And then
I heard, "Draw near, the passes here,"
said in a manner so benign and gentle,
as in our mortal land one cannot hear.
He who addressed us so had open wings,
white as the swans, and he directed us
upward between two walls of the hard
rock. And then he moved his plumes and
fanning us affirmed that those que
lugent would be blessed, their souls
would be possessed of consolation. "What
makes you keep your eyes upon the
ground?" And my g my guide began to say
to me when both of us had climbed a
little past the angel and I what makes
me moved with such misgiving is a new
vision. It has so beguiled me that I
cannot relinquish thoughts of it.
>> Okay. So again this vision has unsettled
Dante. Now he's forced to come to terms
with both the emotion and the vision.
Okay. Keep on going.
>> The one you saw he said that ancient
witch for her alone one must atone
above. You saw how man can free himself
from her. Let that suffice and hurry on
your way. Fasten your eyes upon the lure
that spun by the eternal king with his
great spheres. Just like a falcon who at
first looks down, then when the falconer
has called, bends forward, craving the
food that's ready for him there. So I
became, and so remained until through
the cleft rock that lets one climb
above, I reached the point at which the
circle starts. When I was in the
clearing, the fifth level, my eyes
discovered people there who wept lying
upon the ground, all turned face down.
Mento animea animameha I heard them say
with size so deep that it was hard to
comprehend the words they spoke. Oh
God's elect whose sufferings both hope
and justice make less difficult. Direct
us to the stairway meant for our scent.
If you come here but do not need to be
prostrate and you would find the path
most quickly then keep your right hand
always to the outside. So did the poet
as so did reply come from a little way
ahead. And I hearing that voice reply
learned what was hidden. I turned my
eyes to find my master's eyes. At this,
with a glad sign, he ratified what I had
asked for with my eager eyes. When free
to do as I had wanted to, I moved ahead
and bent over that soul whose words
before had made me notice him, saying,
"Spirit, with them whom weeping ripens,
that without which there's no return to
God, suspend a while for me your greater
care. Tell me, who were you and why are
your backs turned up? And there were I
alive said out, would you have me
beseech them good for you?" and heed to
me. Why heaven turns our backs against
itself, you are to know. But first, she
is quote egoy successor Petri. Between
Cestria and Kio descends a handsome
river, and its name is set upon the
upper portion of my crest. For one
month, and a little more I learned how
the great mantle weighs on him who'd
keep it out of the mire. All other
weight seemed feathers.
Alas, how tardy my conversion was. But
when I had been been named the Roman
shepherd, then I discovered the deceit
of life. I saw that there the heart was
not at rest, nor could I in that life
ascend more high, so that in me love for
this life was kindled. Until that point
I was a squalid soul, for God divided
holy averages. Now, as you see, I'm
punished here for that. When axis here
declared as the purggation of converted
souls, the mountain has no punishment
more bitter. Just as we did not lift our
eyes on high, but set our sight on
earthly things instead, so justice here
impels our eyes toward earth. As a love
of any other good, and thus we lost our
chance for righteous works, so justice
here fetterss our hands and feet and
holds us captive. And for as long as it
may please our just Lord, here will be
outstretched and motionless.
>> Okay, so they are now in a terrorist of
greed or avarice. And they're talking to
Pope Adrien who said that um as Pope he
was extremely ambitious. He did whatever
he could to climb the ladder of power.
And uh now um after he repented he is he
is forced to basically uh lie on the
ground to to focus on the present to
focus on um on Lur himself. Okay. All
right. Keep on going.
Line 127. I'd kneel, wishing to speak,
but just as I began, and through my
voice alone, he sensed that I had meant
to do him reverence. What reason makes
you bend your body so he said, and I to
him, your dignity made conscience sting
me as I stood erect. Brother, straighten
your legs, rise up, he answered. Don't
be mistaken. I, with you and others, am
but a fellow servant of one power. If
you have ever understood the holy sound
of the gospel that says, Make quent.
Then you will see why I have spoken so.
Now go your way. I'd not have you stop
longer. Your staying here disturbs my
lamentations. The tears that help me
ripe in what you mentioned. Beyond. I
have a niece whose name Elijah. She in
herself is good as long as our house by
example brings her not to evil. And she
alone is left to me beyond.
>> Okay. All right. Let's keep on going.
Okay.
KTO 20
against a better will the will fights
weakly. Therefore, to please him, though
against my pleasure, I drew my
unquenched sponge out of the water. I
moved on, and my guide moved through the
unencumbered space, hugging the rock, as
one walks on a wall close to the
battlements. For those whose eyes would
melt down drop by drop, the evil that
possesses all the world were too close
to the edge on the far side. May you be
damned, oh ancient wolf, whose power can
claim more prey than all the other
beasts. Your hungering is steep and ever
ending. Oh heavens, through whose
revolutions many think things on earth
are changed. When will he come? The one
whose works will drive that wolf away.
Our steps were short and slow as we
moved on. I was attentive to the shades.
I heard the sorrow in their tears and
lamentations. Then I by chance heard one
ahead of us crying in his lament, "Sweet
Mary, as a woman without crying in labor
pains," and he continued, "In that
hostel where you had set down your holy
burden, there one could discover just
how poor you were." Following this, I
heard, "Oh good, Fabricius, you ch you
chose as your possessions indigence with
virtue rather than much wealth with
vice. These words have been so pleasing
to me, I moved forward so that I might
come to know the spirit from whom they
had seemed to come." He kept on
speaking, telling the laress of Nicholas
the gifts he gave the maiden so that
they might be honorably wed. Oh soul who
speaks of so much righteousness, do tell
me who you were, I said, and why just
you alone renew these seemly praises.
You're speaking to me will not go unth
than when I return to finish the short
span of that life which now hurries
toward its end. And he I'll tell you,
not because I hope for for solace from
your world, but for such grace as shines
in you before your deaths arrived. I was
the root of the obnoxious plant that
overshadows all the Christian land so
that the fine fruit can rarely rise from
the
>> Okay, so this his name is Hugh Kapad and
he is the founder of the current dynasty
of the Holy Roman Empire. Okay, so his
family now controls the Holy R woman
Roman Empire. As we know, the Holy Roman
Empire is at war with the Vatican, and
this is calling causing all sorts of
chaos throughout the uh the world. So,
he's the root of that obnoxious family
that is now overshadowing all Christian
lands.
Okay. And his name is Hugh Capat. Okay.
All right.
Line 46.
But it but if Dai and Leela and Brush
and Glint have had power, they would
soon take vengeance on it. And this I
beg of him who judges all. The name I
bore beyond was Hugh Cape. Of me was
born the Louise and Phillips by whom
France has been ruled most recently. I
was the son of a Parisian butcher when
all the line of ancient kings was done
and only one am a monk and gray
survived. I found the reigns that ruled
the kingdom tight within my hands. And I
held so much new gained power and
possessed so many friends that to the
widowed crown my own son's head was
elevated. And from him began the
consecrated bones of all those kings
until the giant dowry of Provence
removed all sense of shame within my
house. My line was not worth much but
did no wrong. There its rapine began
with lies and force and then it seized
that it might make men. Pontier and
Norman Normandy and Gaskanany. Charles
came to Italy and for amends made
Corardin a victim and then thrust back
Thomas into heaven for amends. I see a
time not too far off in which another
Charles advances out of France to make
himself and his descendants famous. He
does not carry weapons when he comes,
only the lands that Judas tilted. This
he couches so he twists the punch of
Florence. From this he'll gain not land
just shame and sin which will be all the
heavier for him as he would reckon
lightly such disgrace. The other who
once left his ship as prisoner I see him
sell his daughter bargaining his pirates
haggle over female slaves. Oh Alas, my
house is now your captive. It traffics
in the flesh of it of its own children.
What more is left for you to do to us?
That past and future evil may seem less.
I see the flirt enter an Anani and his
vicor Christ made prisoner. I see him
mock a second time. I see the vinegar
and g renewed and he slain between two
sleeves who are still alive. And I see
the new p pilot one so cruel that still
not say that he without decree carries
his greedy sails into the temple. Oh you
my Lord, when will you let me be happy
on seeing vengeance that concealed make
sweet your anger in your secrecy? What
have I said about the only bride the
Holy Ghost has known? The words that
made you turn to me for commentary.
These words serves as answer to our
prayers as long as it is day. But when
night falls when we recite examples that
are contrary. Then we tell over how Pyon
out of his greedy lust for gold became a
thief and traitor and a parasite. The
wretchedness of Aarish's Midas resulting
from his ravenous request. The
consequence that always makes men laugh.
And each of us recalls the foolish Aiken
how he had robbed the spoil so that the
anger of Joshua still seems to sting him
here. Then we accuse Sapphira and her
husband. We praise the cigodoras
suffered and Palm who killed Polydoris.
Polydoris resounds an infamy around all
this mountain. And finally, what we cry
here is crasses tell us because you know
how does gold taste. At times one speaks
aloud another low according to the
sentiment that goats us now to be more
swift and now more slow. Thus I was not
alone in speaking of the good we sight
by day. But here nearby no other spirit
raised his voice as high. We had already
taken leave of him and were already
struggling to advance along that road as
far as we were able. when I could feel
the mountain tremble like a failing
thing, at which a chill seized me as
cold grips one who goes to meet his
death. Do had surely not been buffeted
so hard before Lana planted there the
nest in which to bear to bear the skies
to your eyes. Then such a shout rose up
on every side that drawing near to me my
master said, "Don't be afraid as long as
I'm your guide."
Gloria in a shel in a shel's day. Oh,
they all cried. So did I understand from
those nearby whose shouted words were
able to be heard. Just like the
shepherds who first heard that song, we
stood but did not move in expectation
until the trembling stopped and the song
was done. Then we took up again our holy
path watching the shades who lay along
the ground who had resumed their
customary tears.
My ignorance has never struggled so has
never made me long so much to know if
memory does not mislead me now as it
seemed then long within my thoughts nor
did I dare to ask. We were so rushed nor
by myself could I discern the cause so
timid pensive I pursued my way.
>> Okay so two points. The first point is
that again there's a lot of symmetry in
Dante. So this mirrors the um um in
paradise where Peter the first pope he
lambasts he criticizes Catholic Church
right well the founder of the current
Holy Roman Empire Hukabad um criticizes
his own family and demands divine
justice divine retribution for all their
crimes. Second point is like um as
they're climbing up the mountain there's
an earthquake. Okay, it shakes. The
reason why the mountain does that is
whenever soul completes his uh pgation
that soul is aditted into heaven and the
the universe celebrates by with with a
earthquake. Okay. To to signify that a
soul has been released and will now
ascend to heaven. Okay. And uh in next
count we will meet the soul.
And I want you to pay careful
attention to how the soul interacts with
Virgil because his soul his name is
Statius. Okay. Statius.
So um the symmetry. Okay. So remember
before uh Don Virgil met Sudello. Okay.
This is Virgil. So Delo is a trodor
uh which is say he is a love he's a poet
of the courtly love tradition and he was
living around the time of Dante okay
maybe the 13th century okay so do you
remember when Virgil met with Sodello
what it was like
yeah they were from the same place what
else
okay and so that bow before Virgil right
and how did Virgil feel about all this?
He was ecstatic, right? He was ecstatic.
Okay. And now what's going to happen is
this. Virgil is going to meet Statius.
And Statius is he is a Latin poet.
Okay, a Latin epic poet very similar to
Virgil. Okay. And Status
worships Virgil.
And how does Virgil feel about this?
What what would you guess?
Yeah, he'd be very he'd be happy as
well, right? Well, if Sord Delo worship
Virgil, you would think another poet
woring Virgil Virgil would have the same
reaction, but it's the opposite
reaction. Okay. He is not happy about
about this. Okay. So, so let's read
count 21. Okay.
>> KTO 21. The natural thirst that never
can be quenched except by water that
gives grace. The drop that the simple
women of Samaria sought tormented me.
Haye spurred me on the path crowded with
souls behind my guide and I felt pity
though their pain was justified. And
here even as Luke records for us that
Christ knew risen from his burial cave
appeared to along his way a shade
appeared and he advanced behind our bags
while we were careful not to trample on
the outstretched crowd. We did not
notice him until he had addressed us
with, "God give you, oh my brother's
peace." We turned at once, then after
offering suitable response, Virgil
began, "And may that just tribunal which
has consigned me to eternal exile place
you in peace within the blessed
assembly." "What?" he excla
exclaimed as we moved forward quickly.
"If God's not deemed you worthy of
ascent, who's guided you so far along
his stairs?" If you observe the signs
the angel traced upon this man, my
teacher said, you'll see plainly he's
meant to reign with all the right
righteous. But since she who spins night
and day, had not yet spun this bool that
clo sets upon the daffin and adjusts for
everyone, his soul, the sister of your
soul and mine in its ascent, could not
alone have climbed here, for it does not
see the way we see. Therefore, I was
brought forth from hell's broad jaws to
guide him in his going. I shall lead him
just as far as where I teach can reach.
But tell me, if you can, why just before
the mountain shook and shout at all of
it, for so it seemed down to its sea
bathed shore. His question threaded so
the needle's eye of my desire that just
the hope alone of knowing left my thirst
more satisfied. The other shade began.
The sanctity of these slopes does not
suffer anything that's without order or
uncustomary. This place is free from
every perturbation what heaven from
itself and in itself receives may serve
us cause here nothing else. Therefore no
rain nor hail, no snow, no due, no
horrost falls here any higher than the
stairs of entry with their three brief
steps. Neither thick clouds nor thin
appear, nor flash of lightning. Thus's
daughter, who so often shifts places in
our world, is absent here. dry vapor
cannot climb up any higher than to the
top of the three steps of which I spoke
where Peter's vicor plants his feet
below that point there may be smaller
ample tremors but here above I know not
why no wind concealed in earth has ever
caused a tremor for it only trembles
here when some soul feels its cleanse so
that it rises or stirs to climb on high
and that shout follows the will alone is
proof of purity and fully free surprise
aes soul into a chain change of dwelling
place effectively. Soul had the will to
climb before, but that will was opposed
by longing to do penance as once to sin
instilled by divine justice. And I who
have lain in this suffering 500 years
and more just now have felt my free will
for a better threshold.
>> Okay, stop. Okay. Um, why are souls
being punished in purgatory?
So had the will to climb before, but
that will was opposed by longitude
penance instilled by divine justice.
Why are souls suffering in purgatory?
What do these three lines mean?
Anyone?
>> Uh Fred? Um, I think it's to test
whether their mindset is true and
whether their mindset is different from
those in hell and that it's changed.
>> Okay, read the lines to yourself. Okay,
and tell me try to paraphrase paraphrase
these lines. Okay,
uh, Anna,
>> I said they had the will to climb
before, but that will was supposed by
longing to do penance. That means they
want to climb but it's not wanting to do
penance. So that's why it's
>> Nope. Nope. What does he mean here?
[clears throat]
Why are they being punished?
>> Yes.
>> Well, they have to cleanse themselves of
their sin because their sin, the weight
of the sin is weighing them down to
climb further.
>> Why do they have to do that though?
>> Well, if they don't cleanse themselves,
then they can't advance, right? It says
who?
>> You
yourself.
>> Excuse me?
>> Yourself.
>> Yourself. Do you understand the idea
here?
>> What this is saying is this. Yes, we
have the desire to climb, but we also
want want to make ourselves worthy of
God. It's not God punishing us. It's
we're punishing ourselves to make
ourselves worthy of God. We are
cleansing ourselves of our sins by doing
penance. Do you understand this idea of
complete free will? No one's making you
do these punishments. You want to these
these punishments because they make you
a better person. And when you face God,
you want to be the best person possible.
You don't want any doubt. You don't want
to have any sin in you. Okay? I mean
like it's like going to the prom and
like you know dressing up really really
nicely. Okay? You want to be the you
want to be your best and that's why you
do penance. That's why you that's why
you suffer. Okay? Keep on going.
70 Thus you heard the earthquake and the
high spirits throughout the mountain as
they praise the Lord. And may he send
them speedily upward. So he so did he
speak to us. And just as joy is greater
when we quench a greater thirst, the joy
he brought cannot be told in words. And
my wise guide, I now can see the net
impeding you. How one slips through and
wide quakes here. And what makes you all
rejoice. And now may it please you to
tell me who you were in your words. May
I find why you've lain here for so many
centuries?
>> Okay, stop. Okay, so so keep this in
mind. Okay, this guy has been doing this
crap for 500 years every single day for
500 years. And now he's completed his
mission. So he is the happiest soul in
the universe at this moment. And he
cannot wait to go meet God. Okay. All he
wants is go meet God. He sees Don and
Virgo like, "Hey guys, get out of the
way, man. I'm I'm going to go to God.
Okay. So that this is his mental state.
This is this is his emotional state.
Okay. Keep keep on going.
>> 82 in that age when the worthy Titus
with help from the highest king avenged
the wounds from which the blood that
Judas sold had flowed.
>> And what year is this? When worthy Titus
avenged the wounds from which the blood
that Judas sold had flowed. Do you guys
know what year this is? Do you guys not
not know your Christian history?
No, it's 70. Do you understand? 70. 70
is the is the year when the Romans
burned down the second temple. Okay.
Titus is the emperor and he burned down
the second temple. All right. And the
Christians believe this is vengeance for
the crucifixion of Jesus. All right.
Keep on going.
>> 85. I had sufficient fame beyond that
spirit replied. I bore the name that
lasts the longest and honors most. But
faith was not yet mine. So gentle was
the spirit of my verse that roame drew
me on. Son of Tulus to her, and there my
brow deserved a crown of myrtle. On
earth my name is still remembered,
Stacius. I sang of thieves and then of
great Achilles. I fell along the way of
that last labor. The sparks that warmed
me. The seeds of my aror were from the
holy fire. The same that gave more than
a thousand poets light and flame. I
speak of the iniative when I wrote
first. It was mother to meet whis nurse.
My work without it would not weigh an
ounce. And to have lived on earth when
Virgil lived. For that I would extend by
one more year the time I owe before my
exiles end.
>> Okay. So, so like what he's saying is
this. Okay. The guy has spent 500 years
in the same crap over and over to make
himself worthy of God. And but there's
one person he admires more than God and
it's Virgil, right? Because Virgil is
the holy fire. And he says, "You know
what? If I had a chance to meet
Virgil just once,
I would keep on going for another year.
Okay.
And Virgil is next to him, right? So,
how is Virgil feeling right now?
He's ecstatic, right? He'd be like, "Oh,
wow. I'm Virgil. Yeah, I'm better than
God. Yeah. Wow. I'm the holy fire. Yeah.
I nursed you. Yeah, that's me, man.
Okay, you understand? All right. And now
we're going to read this and and
appreciate there's no way D could have
created Virgil. He had to summon Virgil.
Okay, because it's too real. Okay, keep
on reading.
>> Verse 103. These words made Virgil turn
to me. And as he turned, his face
through silence said, "Be still." And
yet the power of will cannot do all. For
tears and smiles are both so faithful to
the feelings that have prompted them
that true feeling escapes the will that
would subdue. But I smiled like a man
whose eyes would signal at this. The
shade was silent and he stared where
sentiment is clearest at my eyes.
>> Stop. So okay, this is really important.
Okay, you guys. Do you guys know what's
going on here? This is You have to
actually seen this yourself. You can
actually just make the stuff up.
What's going on here?
Yes. Yes.
>> Virgil is like, "I'm not better than
God. This guy's like too much of a super
fan. Dante, please don't leak it." Yes.
>> But Dante's eyes are so like wide. And
the
>> the the shades just like look at him and
it's like it's like in a pantoime where
he's like he's behind you or something.
Yes.
>> And the shade and he basically betrays
>> Virgil's identity to the shade just with
his expression.
>> So much happens, right? And so much
emotion. so realistic and it's all just
like micro expressions, right? It's just
like the like you know like the um like
Virgil's just like a quick look at him,
right? He doesn't even say anything.
He's like just a quick look like you
know and then Virgil and then Donny's
like like like he can't stop himself.
He's just full of emotion and Satis
looks and says h you [clears throat]
know something. Okay. All right. So this
is all really realistic. All right. Um
keep on going.
Line 112 and said, "So may your trying
labor end successfully. Do tell me why
just now your face showed me the
flashing of a smile. Now I am held by
one side and the other one keeps me
still. The other conjures me to speak.
But when therefore I sigh, my master
knows why and tells me." Do not be
afraid to speak, but speak and answer
what he has asked you to tell him with
such earnestness.
At this I answered, "Ancient spirit, you
perhaps are wondering at the smile I
smiled, but I would have you feel still
more surprised. He who is guide who
leads my eyes on highest, that same
Virgil, from whom you derived the power
to sing of men and of the gods. Do not
suppose my smile had any source beyond
the speech you spoke. Be sure it was
those words you said of him that were
the cause." Now he had bent to kiss my
teacher's feet. But Virgil told him,
"Brother, there's no need. You're a
shade. A shade is what you see." And
rising he now you can understand how
much love burns in me for you. When I
forget our insubstantiality,
treating the shades as one treats solid
things.
>> Okay. All right. Again, the contrast,
right? When where Sudolo meets Virgil,
Virgil tells him right away, "I'm
Virgil." And wow, man, I'm your biggest
fan. And then sort of bows before Virgil
and Virgil's ecstatic. Now Sadius is
like, "I'm your biggest fan." And
Virgil's like, "Oh, okay." Like he
doesn't want him to know I'm Virgil. And
then uh uh Donnie tells him and Stadius
kisses his feet. Okay. He lowers himself
and kisses the feet of Virgil, right?
You remember where where you know um
when Solo talks to Virgil, Virgil's
like, "Yeah, I'll give my autograph and
let's do a selfie." And like, you know,
Virgil is like just loving the moment.
But here, Virgil's like, "Could you
please stop? Just stop, man. Just stop."
Right? Why is Virgil behaving like this?
And and again, it's impossible to create
a Virgil. You have to summon this guy.
Yes.
I think because he realizes that it's
like really hitting in his head that his
poetry is kind of undermining the true
message of the universe. And so like
he's like if I if my work has made
someone at the very height of purgatory
act this way, it just kind of makes him
feel embarrassed. And he's like this
this really isn't what I should have
done. I should not have inspired someone
to behave this way. And it's kind of
making him self-conscious about what he
wanted before.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> And also this act of kissing someone's
feet is what happens in the Bible where
u a woman with her hair she wipes his
feet with oil and kisses his feet. So
it's kind of the same act of worshiping
God in a way. And this guy is literally
going to God in a split second. But he's
like, "Oh, by the way, before that
you're better than God." And then he
makes Virgil like, "Oh my gosh, I hope
this guy doesn't get sent back to
somewhere or like get into trouble or
maybe I don't know."
>> Yeah. Okay. But then why why is Virgil
You're saying like Virgil is a humble
guy, but when Sello
kiss bows before him, Virgil's ecstatic,
right?
There's a paradox here. And the symmetry
shows you there's a paradox to explain
what's going on. And and the answer is
not because, you know, he's embarrassed
at the idea that he's God. He's not. He
wants to be God, right? Um why is he
behaving like this?
Yes.
>> Does he resent that this guy's going to
heaven?
>> Why would he resent this guy going to
heaven? He didn't resent going to
heaven, right? Why would he resent this
guy Stadius going to heaven?
>> He's also a pagan poet.
>> Yeah, right. You understand?
Okay. Remember how awkward it is for
Virgil to meet with Ko, right? Virgil
doesn't really really doesn't want to
talk to Ko and Ko really doesn't want to
talk to him. They hate each other here.
Okay, it's different because that
worships Virgil, but Virgil really
doesn't want to talk to him because
he's a pagan. He's not supposed to go to
heaven. Do you understand?
Like he is a Roman epic poet. He is a
pagan who did not convert. Same as
Virgil.
So
if you're Virgil, you're like, "Uh,
what's going on here?" Right?
Okay. So, let's think about this. Okay.
Um,
we talked how when
Ka when Virgil met Ko,
Virgil just engaged in conic dissonance,
right? He just forgot that Ko is a
pagan. Okay. But here he is able to
recognize the fact that yes, uh, Satis
is a pagan and and I'm a pagan and he's
better than I am. How is he able to do
do this?
Okay. Okay. Um, we're running out of
time, but but but like I I'll throw an
idea out out there for you guys. Okay.
You cannot fool yourself ever. Okay. You
think you can fool yourself, but you
cannot fool yourself ever. Why? Because
you exist in infinite dimensions. And in
some parts you you still know the truth.
In most parts, you may not know the
truth. Does that make sense? Okay,
remember this. Remember this. There's no
way you can ever fool yourself. Maybe
you can fool everyone in the world, but
you cannot fool yourself.
Okay, so Virgo in his heart, he does
know that um it is not true that pagans
cannot go to heaven. It is not true at
all. He knows that. But he does not want
to admit it to Dante because he's more
he's more concerned about his face than
he is about the truth. Okay. Does that
make sense? Uh yes.
>> Yeah. But that still doesn't explain why
he doesn't why he's so humble about him
worshiping him.
>> He's not humble. He's just annoyed.
>> Okay. Okay. So, imagine this. Okay. Like
imagine this. So, we've been here for
two weeks. Okay. And then and then 20
years later, uh, sorry. So what what was
your name?
>> Okay, Ivy. Okay. 20 years later, we Ivy
and I running each other um in New York
City. Who Paris? Who? Who cares? Okay.
But like we're walking the streets and
like and like I'm walking and like she
sees me and like she recognizes me and
says, "Hey, uh, Professor Dang, uh, you
remember me?" I like, "I don't remember
you." Uh, and then she's like, "Oh." And
then she goes on like, "Oh, we we took
the seminar and like, yeah, I remember
you. You you you know, you were shy. You
were very smart." Yeah, sure. And I'm
very happy because she remembers me. And
obviously the course had a huge huge
impact on her. And I ask her, "So Ivy,
uh, what are you doing now?" And she
says, "Oh, I'm teaching Dante at Harvard
or or Yale." Okay.
What do I do now?
Sorry, I have I I have an appointment.
See you later, Ivy. Okay. [laughter] I'm
not Why would I do that? Like, sorry.
Uh, I have an appointment right now.
I'll I'll talk to you later.
Why would I do that?
>> Well, if you Virgil, then I guess you're
jealous. But if you'd be Dante, then
you'd be happy for her, right?
>> Problem. [laughter]
>> That's my problem. You You think?
>> Well, yeah. I mean, you could be happy
for her, but you can also be jealous
that you didn't make it that far. Yeah.
I mean, I think everyone would be a bit
jealous, right? I I And it's not like
Dante or Virgil. It's just like
>> human nature.
>> It's his human nature.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So So again, that's why I say like
Virgil's cannot be crit he can only be
summoned because his reaction is so
human, right?
>> Okay. It's very hard to make something
like this up. you you you you need to
have like seen it yourself
>> to to appreciate this. Okay, does that
does that make sense?
Okay. So, Virgil's really angry and
really jealous at status because status
has reached um heaven. But it's also
it's also um about the b it's kind of
like a burden, right? He says there's no
need your shade. A shade is what you
see. I'm like like he the studies puts
like a burden on Virgil and Virgil can't
really deal with that because like he
can't deal with the with the love of
status.
>> Yeah. And and it's also like absurd,
right? You're both like shades, right?
So if you kneel down, I can't actually
feel you kissing my feet like like this
is absurd. Espec
>> I guess the other thing other than
summoning Virgil that he could have done
is in real life if Dante met Beric's
husband. So the historically she mar she
died young but married like a banker.
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> So it's like if the banker came to maybe
Dante felt this for one second like the
banker came to Dante and like I'm your
biggest fan of all time and he's like
well you married my one true love and
then she died so like h how much can you
I don't really care that you're my fan
or it upsets you.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's just human nature.
Okay. And that's why the line comedy is
such literature because it's something
that that resonates with you. Okay. you
just feel it's true and it gives you
tremendous insight into yourself as well
as uh human nature and and you know it's
just a natural reaction right
um okay the other thing I will point out
is okay we we'll keep on reading 21 okay
oh 22 now yeah sure
>> kto 22 the angel now has left behind us
he who had directed us to the six
terraas having erased one pee that
scarred my face he had declared that
Those who long for justice are blessed.
And his voice concluded that message
with situ without the rest. And while I
climbed behind the two swift spirits,
not laboring at all, for I was lighter
than I had been along the other stairs.
Virgil began love that is kindled by
virtue virtue will in another find
reply. As long as that love's flame
appears without, so from the time when
juvenile descending among us, and hell's
limbo had made plain the fondness that
you felt for me, my own benevolence
towards you has been much richer than
any ever given to a person one has not
seen. Thus now these stairs seem short,
but tell me, and as a friend, forgive me
if excessive cander lets my reigns
relax, and as a friend exchange your
words with me, how is it that you found
within your breast a place for avarice
when you possess the wisdom you had
nurtured with such care? These words at
first brought something of a smile to
St. Sass, then he answered, "Every word
you speak to me is a dear sign of love.
Indeed, because true causes are
concealed, we often face deceptive
reasoning and things provoke perplexity
in us. Your question makes me sure that
you're convinced, perhaps because my
circle was the fifth, that in the life I
once lived, avar had been my sin. Note
then that I was far from avarest. It was
my lack of measure. Thousands of months
have punished. And if I had not
corrected my assessment by my
understanding what your verses meant
when you as if outraged by human nature
exclaimed, why cannot you, a holy hunger
for gold, restrain the appetite of
mortals? I'd now while rolling weights
no sorry joust. Then I became aware that
hands might open too wide like wings and
spending of and of this as of my other
sins I did repent. How many are to rise
again with heads cropped close whom
ignorance prevents from reaching
repentance in and at the end of life and
know that when a sin is countered by
another fault directly opposite to it
then here both sins see their green
wither thus I join those who pay for
avaras in my pgation though what brought
me here was prodigality its opposite now
when you sang the savage wars of those
twin sorrows of jastice of the singer of
the collic poems it does not seem from
those notes struck by you and Cleo there
that you had not you that you had yet
turned faithful to the faith without
which righteousness works that do not
suffice.
If that is so, then what son or what
candles drew you from darkness, so that
in their wake you set yourselves behind
the fishermen? And he to him, you were
the first to send me to drink within
harnesses caves, and you the first who
after God enlighten me. You did as he
who goes by night and carries the lamp
behind him. He's of no help to his own
self, but teaches those who follow. when
you declared the ages are renewed
justice and man's first time on earth
return from heaven a new progeny
descends through you I was a poet and
through you a Christian but that you may
see more plainly plainly I'll set my
hand to color what I sketch
>> okay all right so um so Virgil asks
Sadius why are you in the terrace of
avarice and sadius replies okay you may
think that I was greedy in life but I
was the opposite. In fact, I was
wasteful. But it's the laws of nature
that one extreme, the two extremes are
basically the same thing. Okay? So if
you are really greedy but if you are
very wasteful, it's the same thing. And
so the punishment is the same. Okay. And
then um what Virgil asked him is
how did you come to this place? Because
in Virgil's understanding, only
Christians [snorts] are allowed access
to
heaven. And what Virgil, sorry, what
Sadius says is, "Well, I converted
secretly." Yeah, I converted secretly.
Um, and
who convinced him to convert to
Christianity?
>> Poet poets. And to you, a Christian?
>> Yeah, this is a paradox, right? We know
Virgil is not a Christian. In fact, he's
an anti-Christian almost.
And so, Sus is saying like, "For you, I
become a poet." And we know because he
keeps on quoting the Iniad. Okay? He's
just memorized the Iniad. He keeps on
quoting the Iniad. He says like, "F you,
I've been able to become a Christian."
But we know the Iniad.
How does this make any sense?
Yeah. Yeah.
using an the structure of empire that
has kind of made it kind of spread so
powerfully.
>> Okay.
>> Maybe I don't.
>> Okay. Anyone else?
>> Yes.
The mercy of Christ becomes so much more
apparent that it's the true way and it's
like the divine truth when you're
immersed in the anid. So in the final
moment when a near not the final but the
major moment where Nas kills Turnis if
you're really moved by that and you
meditate on that moment for a long time
and you think what would it have to be
for Turnis for for Anas not to kill
Turnis what mercy would he have had to
have that would have turned you made you
look for a preacher that would have
changed your mind.
>> Yeah that's that's great that's
fantastic. Okay. And that's exactly what
Satis is saying here. I read the Iniad
and the themes and ideas that you um
tell in the Iniad convince me that I
must turn to Christ.
But okay, didn't Virgil write the Iniad?
So why didn't why didn't Virgil
embrace Christianity the way that
Statist embraced Christianity? Virgil is
a poet.
Is that just a weer? What's going on
here?
>> It's like he changed the ending
like Virgil ruined the ending of the
Aniid which made it so powerful for
empire but ruined what could have been
the Christian prelude.
>> Yeah, but but you just said that it
moved Stadius to convert to
Christianity. What's going on here?
>> It can move everybody except Virgil.
He's like the unluckiest guy in the
world. Where
>> is this luck?
>> Well, maybe it's I don't know.
>> Anyone else? He also follows saying in
74 that but that you may see more plain
I set my hand to color what I sketch.
>> Oh no no no he he's trying to explain
his life.
>> Oh okay.
>> Yeah yeah yeah. He he'll explain his
life story and how the exact details of
how he converted.
>> Okay. So let's try to figure this out.
Okay. All right. So remember the poets
are channeling the divine fire, the holy
fire. Okay. And the poetry is meant to
um capture the holy fire so that others
can be illuminated by it. Okay? So he's
trying to create this vessel.
Um but we have free will so we can do
whatever we want. And then Virgil became
seduced by power. So he turned this
vessel into a weapon for empire. Okay.
But but the so bas basically before the
vessel was meant to be like a um like a
glass where everyone can just feel the
light but now it's like this bronze
vessel a weapon. Okay. But the holy fire
is so strong that there are things that
leak out and if you're willing if you
are a perceptive enough reader you're
able to still feel that light and that
light will draw you to Christianity.
Does that make sense? Okay.
But the poet has committed evil and sin
by trapped in the holy fire. And so the
poet um
um is convinced that this vessel that
this weapon he's created is actually for
good reasons. And so this conissonance
blinds the poet from seeing the holy
light. Does that make sense guys? Okay.
That's right. Stadius can be converted
by the Iniad, but Virgil cannot be
converted by the Iniad.
Okay, Fred Fred, did you want to add
something or
>> it just I keep my mind keeps going back
to the moment when Anias sees Palace's
sword belt and in the Anid that's so um
the Anid portrays like Anias he's really
sad he's really upset he's so close to
showing mercy to Turnis but then he sees
the sword belt of his friend this young
guy palace who Turnis had killed and
it's almost it's like the divine light
leaking out it's like Virgil going, I
wish I could. I wish I had written it. I
wish I want to write it that Anias shows
mercy.
>> But it's almost like seeing the sword
belt of one of your comrades is the is
empire. It's like the people that come
before you, you're trying to propagate
your empire for them, and that's what
makes him change. So, it's like Virgil's
trying to say that he wished he wished
he hadn't written that, but he just did.
>> Yeah. And and Virgil did say he didn't
he wish he didn't write that because he
wanted to burn the manuscript, right?
So, so yeah. So, so that's what's going
on here. Okay. All right. Let's let's
keep on reading.
>> Line 76. Disseminated by the messages
messengers of the eternal kingdom. The
true faith by then had penetrated all
the world. And the new preachers
preached in such accord with what you'd
said, and I have just repeated that I
was drawn into frequenting them. Then
they appeared to me to be so saintly
that when Domian persecuted them, my own
laments accompanied their grief. And
while I could, as long as I had live, I
helped them, and their honest practices
made me disdainful of all other sex.
Before, within my poem, I'd led the
Greeks unto the streams of thieves, I
was baptized. But out of fear, I was a
secret Christian, and for a long time
showed myself as pagan. For this
half-heartedness, for more than four
centuries, I circled the fourth circle.
And now, may you who lifted up the lid
that hid from me the good of which I
speak while time has left us as we
climb, tell me, where's our ancient
terrace? and chicelius and ploutus where
as various if you know tell me if
they're damned and in what quarter all
these imperious I and many other my
guide replied are with that great to
whom the muses gave their gifts in
greatest measure our place is the blind
prison its first circle and there we
often talk about the mountain where
those who were our nurses always dwell
is with us Antifon Simony and Agathon as
well as many other Greeks who once wore
laurel upon their brow and There of your
own people once the antiggony deili is
mani sad still argia as she was there
one can see the woman who showed langia
and there to to roia's daughter there's
fetus and with her sisters there damia
both poets now were silent once again
intent on their surroundings they were
free of stairs and walls with day's
first four handmaidaidens already left
behind and with the fifth guiding the
chariot pull and lifting it so that its
horn of flame rose is always higher. My
master said, "I think it's time that we
turn our right shoulders toward the
terrace edge, circling the mountain in
the way we're used to." In this way,
habit served us as a banner. And when we
chose that path, our fear was less
because that worthy soul gave his
two were in the lead. I walked alone
behind them, listening to their
colloquy, which taught me much
concerning poetry. But their delightful
conversation soon was interrupted by a
tree that blocked our path. Its fruits
were fine. Their scent was sweet, and
even as a fur tree tapers upward from
branch to branch, that tree there
tapered downward so as I think to ward
off any climber.
Upon our left, where wall enclosed her
path, rich bright running water fell
from the high rock and spread itself
upon the leaves above. When the two
poets had approached the tree, a voice
emerging from within the leaves cried
out, "This food shall be denied to you."
Then it cried, Mary's care was for the
marriage feast being seemly and
complete, not for her mouth, which now
would intercede for you. And when they
when they drank of old, the Roman women
were satisfied with water, and young
Daniel through his disdain of food
acquired wisdom. The first age was as
ferris gold. When hungry men found the
taste of acorns good, when thirsty they
found that that every little stream was
nectar. When he was in the wilderness,
the Baptist had fed on nothing more than
honey locusts. For this he was made
great, as glorious as in the gospel is
made plain to you.
>> Okay. So they arrive in the terrace of
gluttony. And uh the glutton in the
terrace of gluttony there's a tree with
lots of fruit and um the sinners just
look at it and they're not able to touch
it and they become much more hungry and
as eminated over time. Okay. So really
important point is there's a paradox
right? How is Stadius who is a pagan how
is he able to ascend heaven and what he
tells Virgil is well I converted
secretly no one knows this but I
converted secretly and yeah that was
lazy of me that that was slothful that
show lack of faith and that's why I was
in the terrorist of sloth for four
centuries and it seems as though this
relieves the paradox right the softs
paradox well because he converted
secretly well the problem here Okay,
let's go to paradise 20. Paradise 20,
everyone. And in paradise 20,
there is going to be to be an eagle.
Okay. And in this eagle are the great
kings of time. Okay. Including David.
And one of them, one of these
uh people
is Rifus. Okay.
Rifus.
And Riftheus
is a Trojan.
What's the problem, guys?
Why is this a problem? Why is this a
paradox?
Yes.
Yeah. So, there's no way this could have
happened, right? Because this this is
not just before the time of Jesus. It's
also before the time of the Hebrews,
man. So, like this is like really
confusing now for us. Okay. So sis, can
we read um paradise 20 please? Can can
we go go please? Uh 20 and we'll skip to
um uh 37. Okay.
>> And this is the ego of light talking to
Dante saying like who is the most worthy
to be inside me? Okay.
37.
>> He who gleams in the center of my eyes
pupil. He was the singer of the Holy
Spirit who bore the ark from one town to
another. Now he has learned the merit
will can earn. His song had not been
spurred by grace alone, but his own will
in part had urged him on. Of those five
flames that arching for my brow, he who
is nearest to my beak is one who
comforted the widow for her son. Now he
has learned the price one pays for not
following Christ through his experience
of this sweet life and of its opposite.
>> Okay, so there are certain individuals
within this ego who are divine and holy.
Okay, the first one is David. That makes
sense. Second one is Trajan. Um, who is
who was a Roman emperor. Uh, let's keep
on going.
>> Um,
>> 49.
>> 49. And he whose place is next on the
circumference of which I speak along the
upward arc delayed his death through
truthful penitence. Now he has learned
that the eternal judgment remains
unchanged. Though worthy prayer below
makes what falls due today take place
tomorrow.
>> Okay. So uh Trajan convert to
Christianity. Yes. Uh okay that makes
sense. Keep on going.
>> 55. The next two who follows one whose
good intention bore evil fruit to give
place to the shepherd with both the lost
and me made himself Greek. Now he has
learned that even though the world be
ruined by the evil that derives from his
good act, that evil does not harm him.
He he whom you see along the downward
arc was William and the land that mourns
his death for living Charles and
Frederick now laments. Now he has
learned how heaven loves the just ruler.
And he would show his this outwardly as
well, so radiantly visible. Who in the
world below would hold that he who was
the fifth among the lights that formed
the circle was the Trojan Rifus. Now he
has learned much that the world cannot
discern of God's own grace, although his
sight cannot divine not reach its
deepest sight. As if it were a lark at
large in air, a lark that sings at at
first and falls and then falls still.
content with final sweetness that
fulfills such things.
>> Okay, stop. Okay. All right. So, again,
this makes sense until we get to the
fifth and last person who who is Rifus.
And what the ego says is like um
okay well Rifus
uh he was born before the time of of
Jesus so he could not convert it. Trajan
was born after Jesus so he could have
converted. How do we explain Rifus? This
is a huge paradox, right? Again, it's
one thing for Stadius to convert
secretly and then he goes to purgatory.
Then through 500 years of penance, he
climbs to heaven. But up here in
paradise is Rifus, a Trojan who was born
before the time of both the Hebrews and
of Jesus, and he makes it to heaven. How
is this possible?
Okay. Yeah. Um uh yes.
>> I mean that just shows like V uh Dantis
democratic sense, right? Everyone can
make it to heaven if they really will it
like if they really want to.
>> Okay. Okay. But Rifus could not have
wield it because he didn't know heaven
exists, right? He didn't know Jesus
exists. He didn't know God exists. He
doesn't know that stuff.
>> Yeah. But you can still follow your
intuition and know what's good and
right. Like you don't need the knowledge
of heaven. You just need to be a good
human.
>> Exactly. Okay. Does that make sense?
Yeah. So that's what Donnie is saying is
it's revolutionary. Okay. It can really
counteracts the point that Virgil makes
which is like you have to be a Christian
in order to make it to heaven. So, let
me ask you this question. Why is Virgil
so adamant? Why is he so focused on this
one rule? And why is D like actually no?
>> Because it's basically his mask or
excuse of not making it to heaven. It's
like, oh, they kind of excluded me
because I was just born at the wrong
time. Okay, it's not my fault. Like
Jesus was so much later than me. It's,
you know, taking the blame off him. But
then now everybody else way older than
him before him who had never met Jesus
or the concept of Hebrews, they went to
heaven. It's like kind of a slap in the
face. It's like you're just basically
not a good enough guy. Okay. Like to
make it to heaven. Face it guy. Like
don't you know?
>> Yeah.
>> Fine excuse.
>> Exactly. So he's constantly excusing
himself, right? He rather again burn in
hell than just admit he's wrong. Um
Rifus is interesting because who creates
Rifius's character?
Virgil
Dante only knows about Rifius because
speaks of of of Virgil. C can we go
Google this? We'll Google Rifus and see
what comes up. Okay.
>> Oh,
okay.
>> Okay. Okay. So, so, so, so just read uh
not that the the sorry uh go back.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Just just do
>> sure just just read that part. Okay.
>> Rifus was a Trojan hero in the name of a
figure from the Anita Virgil.
>> Okay, that this is why we know this guy.
Virgil created this guy.
>> Okay, and quite honestly, all Virgil
says is he is the most virtuous of all
of all the Trojans. That's that's entire
line in in the Iniad. He's not a major
character.
Okay. So So can we write what what V
what Virgil writes?
Just just open up. Yeah.
Virgil writes, "Uniquely the most just
of all the Trojans, the most faithful
preserver of equity, but the gods
decided otherwise."
>> Okay, so this is a jab at Virgil, right?
V Virgil says, "Yeah, he's he's he's the
wisest, the the most just of the um
Trojans, and uh the gods didn't care."
And D's like, "No, the gods do care.
Thank you very much. If you are
righteous, if you are just, if you're
virtuous, you will always go to heaven
regardless of time and space, regardless
of your belief. Okay? Regardless what
Virgil says.
Okay? So again, the divine comedy is a
rejection of Virgil, but it's also born
of Virgil. Okay? It's it's like the
father-son relationship. Okay. Let's uh
go back to um
uh purgatory.
Uh one, I think. Are we done with this
one?
>> Yes.
>> No, we're done.
>> 23.
Okay. So, you guys see how clever Dante
is, right? He doesn't tell you outright,
but he gives you like these clues, and
once you put the clues together, the
answer is pretty obvious. Okay.
>> Console 23. When I was peering so
intently through the green boughs, like
a hunter who so used would waste his
life in chasing after birds, my more
than father said to me, "Now come, son,
for the time our journey can commit as
to be used more fruitfully than this." I
turned my eyes, and I was no less quick
to turn my steps. I followed those two
sages whose talk was such my going
brought no less, and there labia man
domin.
Oh gentle father, what is this I hear?
asked, and he perhaps their shades who
go loosening the knot of what they owe.
Even as pensive pilgrims do, who when
they've overtaken folk unknown to them
along the way, will turn but will not
stop. So overtaken us, they had come
from behind, but were more swift. A
crowd of souls devout and silent, looked
at us in wonder. Each shade had dark and
hollow eyes. Their faces were pale and
so emaciated that their taught skin took
its shape from bones beneath. I don't
believe that even Ion had been so dried
down to his very hide by hunger when his
fast made him fear most thinking I told
myself I see the people who lost
Jerusalem when Mary plunged her beak
into her son the orbits their of their
eyes seemed like a ring that's lost its
gems and he who in the face of man would
read oh mo would hear have recognized
the m who if he knew not how would have
believed believe that longing born from
odor of a tree, odor of water could
reduce soul. So I was already wondering
what had so famished them, for I had not
learned the reason for their leanness
and sad scuff scurf. When there a shade,
his eyes deep in his head turned toward
me, staring steadily, and then he cried
aloud, "What grace has granted me." I
never would have recognized him by his
face, and yet his voice made plain to me
what his appearance had obliterated. The
spark rekindled in me everything I knew
about those altered features. Thus I
realized it was FZ's face. "Ah, don't
reproach me for the dried out scabs that
stain my skin," he begged. "Nor for the
lack of flesh on me, but do tell me the
truth about yourself. Do tell me who
those two souls there are, those who are
escort escorting you. May you not keep
yourself from speaking to me."
>> Okay, stop. Okay. All right. So, Fer Bon
Bonati Fer
Bonati, he is actually uh Donniey's
childhood best friend. He's also a poet
and um they enjoy making fun of each
other through their poetry. Uh Fer's
sister is Marta. Okay, we met Picarda in
heaven. His brother is also Corso. Okay,
Corso is the brother who tr who adopted
Picarda from the convent because Corso
was intent on power and Corso will
eventually die and burn in hell. Okay,
but Feresi is a very important
character.
Line 55. Your face which I once wept on
when you died, I answered him. now gives
me no less cause for sad lament seeing
you so deformed but tell me for God's
sake what has unleashed you so don't
make me speak while I'm amazed he who's
distracted answers clumsily and he to me
from the eternal counsel the water and
the tree you left behind receive the
power that makes me waste away all of
these souls who grieving sing because
their appetite was gluttonous and thirst
and hunger here resent by themselves the
fragrance of the fruit and of the water
that sprayed through that green tree
kindles s us craving for food and drink
and not once only as we go around the
space our pains renewed. I speak of
pain, but I should speak of solace. For
we're guided to those trees by that same
longing that had guided Christ when he
had come to free us through the blood he
shed and in his joy joyousness called
out Eli. And I to him for that day when
you exchanged the world for better life
until now less than five years have
evolved. And if you waited for the
moment when the power to sin was gone
before you found the hour of the good
grief that suckers us and wets us once
again to God. How have you come so
quickly here? I thought to find you down
below where time must pay for time. And
he to me it is my Nella who with her
abundant tears has guided me to drink
the sweet bor wood of tor to torments.
She with size and prayers devout has set
me free of that slope where one waits
and has freed me from circles underneath
the circle. She my gentle widow whom I
loved most dearly was all the more
beloved and praised by God as she's more
alone in her good works. For even the
barbagia of Sardinia is far more modest
in its women than that barbagia when I
left her. Oh sweet brother, what would
you have had me say? A future times
already visible to me a time not too far
off from now when from the pulpit it
shall be forbidden to those immodest
ones, Florentine women to go displaying
bosoms with bare paps. What ordinances
spiritual civil were ever needed by
barbarian or sessan women to make them
go covered? But if those shameless ones
had certain knowledge of what s swift
heavens readying for them, then they
would have mouths open now to howl. For
if our foresight here does not deceive
me, they'll be sad before the cheeks of
those whom lullabies can now appease
grow beards. Ah, brother, do not hide
things any longer. You see that I am not
alone, for all these people stare at
where you veil the sun. At this I said
to him, if you should call to mind what
you have been with me, and I with you,
remembering now will still be heavy. He
who precedes me turned me from that life
some days ago when she who's the sister
of him. I pointed to the son was showing
her roundness to you. It is he whose led
me through the deep night of the truly
dead with this true flesh that follows
after him.
His help has drawn me up from there
climbing and circling around this
mountain which makes straight you whom
the world made crooked. And he says that
he will bear me company until I reach
the place where Beatrice is. There I
must remain without him. It is Virgil
who speaks to me in this way and I point
it to him. This other is the shade for
whom just now your kingdom caused its
very its every slope to tremble as it
freed him from itself.
>> So D meets his childhood best friend and
he's ecstatic to see fors again, right?
But he's but he's confused and he asked
for um I thought you were supposed to
wait in enter purgatory for a long long
time. It's been five years since 5 years
since your death and already you made it
really high up and like how [snorts] is
this possible for essay and and what
does he Fors say
his his his widow Nella right prayed
every day for him and because Nella was
particularly virtuous and beloved by God
then uh Forza was able to climb up very
very high okay and this explains why
there are certain infants in paradise,
right? Because their parents were really
virtuous and prayed for them every
single day. Okay. Um
let's keep on going to count 24, please.
Our talking did not slow our pace. Our
pace not slowing our talking, but
conversing, we moved quickly like a boat
of fair wind drives. and recognizing
that I was alive, the shades they seemed
to be things twice dead, drew amazement
from the hollows of their eyes. And I,
continuing my telling, added, "Perhaps
he's more slow in his ascent than he
would had he not met the other. But tell
me, if you can, where is Picarda? And
tell me if among those staring at me, I
can see any person I should note." My
sister, and I know not whether she was
greater in her goodness or her beauty on
High Olympus is in triumph. She rejoices
in her crown already. He began then
added, "It is not forbidden to name each
s shade here. Abstinence has eaten away
our faces." And he pointed, "This is
Bonjuna. Bonjuna deuca, the one beyond
him, even more emaciated than the rest,
had clasped the holy church. He was from
tour, his fast purchased boss, eels,
Renachia's wine. And he named many
others one by one, and at their naming
they all seemed content, so that for
this no face was overcast. I saw their
teeth were biting emptiness, both
Ubaldin de laila and Bon Bonaface, who
shepherded so many with his staff. I saw
Messer Marquees, who once had more ease
less dryness, drinking it poorly, and
yet could never satisfy his thirst. But
just as he looks and then esteems one
more than another, so did I praise him
of Luca, for he seemed to know me
better. he murmured. Something like
Gentuka was what I heard from the place
where he could feel the wound of justice
that denudes them so. Oh soul, I said,
who seemed so eager to converse with me,
do speak so that I hear you, for speech
may satisfy both you and me. He
answered, although men condemn my city,
there is a woman born. She wears no veil
as yet because of whom you will find it
pleasing. You're to journey with this
prophecy as if as if there is something
in my murmuring you doubt. Events
themselves will bear me out. But tell me
if the man whom I see here is he who
brought the new rhymes forth. Beginning
ladies who have intelligence of love. I
answered, I'm one who when love breathes
in me takes takes note. What he within
dictates I in that way without would
speak and shape. Oh brother, now I see.
He said the knot that kept the notary gu
and me short of the sweet new manner
that I hear. I clearly see how your
pence follow closely behind him who
dictates, and certainly that did not
happen with our pens, and he who sets
himself to feriting profoundly can find
no other difference between the two
styles. He fell still contentedly, even
as birds that winter on the Nile at
times will slow and form a flock in air,
then speed their flight, and form a
file. So all the people who are mere
moved much much more swiftly, turning
away their faces, hurrying their pace
because of leanness and leanness and
desire.
And just as he who's tired of running
lets his comrades go ahead and slows his
steps until he sees the panting of his
chest, so did Ferz let the holy flock
pass by and move behind with me, saying,
"How long before I shall see you again?"
I do not know, I said, how long I will
live. And yet, however quick is my
return, my longing for these shores
would have me here sooner. Because the
place where I was set to live is
daybyday deprived of good and seems
along the way to wretched ruin. Do not
be vexed, he said, for I can see the
guiltiest of all dragged by a beast's
tail to the valley where no sin is
purged. At every step, the beast moves
faster, always gaining momentum till it
smashes him and leave his body leaves
his body squally and death.
those wheels. And here he looked up at
the sky. Do not have long to turn before
you see plainly what I can't tell you
more openly. Now you remain behind, for
time is costly here in this kingdom. I
should lose too much by moving with us
thus at equal pace. Just as a horseman
sometimes gallops out, leaving behind
his troop of riders, so that he may gain
the honor of the first clash, so with
longer strides did he leave us. And I
remained along my path with those two
who were such great marshals of the
world. And we he'd gone so far ahead of
us, and that my eyes that my eyes
strained to follow him, just as my mind
was straining after what he'd said. The
branches of another tree heavy with root
a life with grain appeared to me nearby
just past a curve where I turned had
turned. Beneath the tree I saw shades
lifting hands crying I know not what up
toward the branches like little eager
empty-handed children who beg but he of
whom they beg does not reply but to
provoke their longing. He holds high and
does not hide the thing they want. Then
they departed as if disabused, and we
immediately reached that great tree
which turns aside so many prayers and
tears. Continue on, but don't draw close
to it. There is a tree above from which
Eve ate, and from that tree above this
plant was raised. Among the boughs, a
voice I know not whose spoke so. thus
drawing close Virgil Stacius and Ished
on along the side that rises. It said,
"Remember those with double chests, the
miserable ones born of the clouds, whom
the battled when they gorged themselves,
and those whom Gideon refused as
comrades, those Hebrews who had drunk
too m avidly when he came down the hills
to Midian." So keeping close to one of
that road's margins, we moved ahead,
hearing of gluttonly, it had since
prepaid by sorry penalties. Then with
more space along the lonely path a
thousand steps and more had brought us
forward, each of us meditating
wordlessly.
What are you thinking of you three who
walk alone? A sudden a sudden voice
called out at which I started like a
scared young animal. I raised my head to
see who it might be. No glass or metal
ever seen within a furnace was so
glowing or so red as one I saw who said,
"If you'd ascend, then you must turn at
this point. For whoever would journey
unto peace must pass this way. But his
appearance had deprived me of my sight.
So that as one who uses hearing as
guide, I turned and followed my two
teachers. And like the breeze of May
that heralding that dawn the dawn
dawning of the day, when it steeped in
flowers and in grass stirs fragrantly,
so did I feel the wind that blew against
the center of my brow and clearly sent
the movement of his wings, the air's
ambrosia. And then I heard, "Blessed are
those who embrace illumin so that in
their breast the love taste does not
awake too much desire, whose hungering
is always in just measure."
>> So So do
this is your dream,
right? You told us you had a dream of a
tree calling to you, but there's a river
that blocked the way and the tree was
talking to you.
And now we have a similar situation,
right? where this is a tree with the
fruit of the knowledge of good and evil
and everyone can only look at it
longingly and the tree talks to them but
you can never eat the fruit.
What do you think?
Is your dream si similar to what's going
on?
So, so why do you think you have to have
the dream?
>> No, no, no, no. I'm saying like why do
you think you had the dream?
>> I'm still trying to figure it out. But
like if I if I if I have to take a guess
that like I'm looking for a change in my
life right now and
um and I've been thinking about like
this uh the all the classes that I I
took during this this this seminar and
about like imagination and love and and
especially like um during
like I I feel I felt like pretty
comfortable when we in the paradise
right but as but like once we enter the
hill and the purgatory
I
it made me to reflect on my past life
about all the wrongs I did to other
people and stuff. So maybe it's a way
for me to seek redemption or something
like that.
>> Do you think when you had the dream you
saw the future?
Did you see the future in your dream?
Well, do do you know his dream, Brad?
>> I think he had what we might call
momentum in Indra's net. So, like all of
the images we've been learning before
primed him and that his dream basically
preempted what would follow in the poem
because the poem was so close a copy of
these wonderful images that are in
Indra's net. like everything we had been
thinking about had led him up to this
and it's like he just turned up to class
early, you know, in in a sense.
>> Okay, that's interesting.
>> It didn't feel like
I'm like experience the future.
I mean, the sense of time seems like
didn't exist in the in my dream.
>> Right. Right. Right.
>> It's like all past and present and
future matched up together.
>> Right. But but like that's what we said
in the universal unconscious, right?
It's beyond time and space. It's all
happening at once.
Okay.
Are you surprised at all by this? You
you you dreamt
of this scene
yesterday
and now we're talking about this scene
and we're trying to decipher your dream
through this scene.
Uh,
not surprised honestly, but like
I feel I feel it's like it's destined.
It's it's destinated to be like this.
Has anyone had a dream that was
basically of the future?
So, this happens to you a lot. Okay.
G give us an example.
Uh
it's
nothing like special but
uh sometimes it's just like uh when I
enter like a building a hall or I just
had a lunch with with a with a like with
a with a stranger and it just clicks. I
was like oh I I knew what would happen
like five five minutes later or like uh
like an hour later. Yeah. Okay, Fred, do
>> I just had some very strange ones where
like I had an ex-girlfriend and I dreamt
that her body had become like fully
fertile and she was trying to feed me
from her enlarged breasts and then like
2 days I had not spoken to her for many
months and then 2 days later she like
calls me and it was like one of the
craziest moments of my life.
>> Yeah, but this happens a lot.
Well, when I count it as a lot, it it
feels like this many.
>> I'm saying like what I meant is I'm I'm
not saying it happens to a lot to you,
but I'm saying like it's actually pretty
common in in the world, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I went to Malaysia the night before I
visited my uh godmother's house. She had
a dream from God saying, "I'm going to
bring you a daughter." And she was 40
something. She's like, "There's no way
I'm going to have a daughter now. I'm
not going to be Sarah." And next day I
came to her house. She's like, "Ah,
you're the kid." And so they accepted me
immediately and then she told me long
after about this trip.
>> Yeah. I mean, like, isn't it very common
um that you think of a friend, right,
and then your friend calls you the next
day or next week? It's very common, man,
right? We we've all had this experience.
You're thinking of someone that person
just calls you and says, "Hey, I was
thinking of you and I wanted to blah
blah blah." Okay. All right. So, again,
this gives credit to the idea of the
universal unconscious.
All right. Uh okay, let's keep on going.
>> KTO 25. The hour when climbers cannot
pause had come. The sun had left to
Taurus the meridian and night had left
it to the scorpion. Therefore, like one
who will not stop but moves along his
path no matter what he sees. If he's
goatated by necessity, we made our way
into the narrow gap and one behind the
other took the stairs so straight that
climbers there must separate. And as the
fledgling stork will lift its wings
because it wants to fly but dares not
try to leave the nest and lets its wing
drop back. So I with my desire to
question kindled then spent arrived as
far as making ready to speak. But my
dear father though our steps were
hurrying did not stop talking for he
said the iron of the arrows touched the
long bow le let the shaft of speech fly
off. Then I had confidence enough to
open my mouth and ask him, "How can one
grow lean when there's never need for
nourishment?"
>> Okay, so this is a great question. Okay,
so
saw these shades becoming much more
emissiated. Okay, and D is like, "Wait a
minute here. They have no bodies, right?
Therefore, you have no need for food.
So why would you become emaciated? How
do you starve as a soul? This makes no
sense. Okay, that's a question that
Dante has. All right, so uh let's see
what Virgil says.
>> Line 22. If you recall how Male was
consumed, he said just when the fire
brand was bent, this won't be hard to
understand. And if you think how though
your body swift, your image of the
mirror captures it, then what perplexed
will seem to you transparent, but that
your will to know may be appeased
heistas. And I'll I call on him and ask
that he now be the healer of your
doubts.
>> Okay. So what Virgil was saying is well
so Meliger Meliger is a story where uh
Meliger
um he his soul is kept alive by a
firewood and as long as this firewood is
extinguished. So as long as this
firewood is unbroken, then he lives. So
what the mother does is hide the
firewood so he can never be broken. But
Miger then does something so outrageous
that the mother wants to kill him. So
then she finds a firewood and then burns
it down and then Miger dies. Okay. So
what what he's saying is what you what
you have to understand is a
correspondence of things. Okay? The
correspondence between the body, the
soul and the spirit. So that one thing
happens to to to one then the other then
the other thing happens to the other.
Okay. So if your soul is starving then
your body is starving. If your body is
starving so is your soul starving.
But
what's the problem with this
explanation?
The body's gone, right? So this is
really confusing. So he doesn't really
answer and he recognizes he doesn't
really answer. So he he says, "Let
Stadius answer." Okay. All right. Sus,
you try now. All right.
>> Line 31. If I explain eternal ways to
him, Sass replied, "While you are
present here, let my excuse be, I cannot
refuse you." Then he began, "If son your
mind receives and keeps my word, then
what I say will serve as light upon the
how that you have asked. The thirsty
veins drink up the perfect blood. But
not all of that blood. a portions left
like leings that are taken from the
table within the heart. That part
acquires power to form all of another's
human limbs. As blood that flows through
veins feeds one's own limbs, digested
yet again that part descends to what is
best not named. From there it drips into
the natural receptacle upon another's
blood. The two bloods makes one ready to
be passive and one active because of
perfect place. The heart prepared them.
The act of having reached the passive
starts to work. First it coagulates and
then quickens the matter it has made
more dense having become a soul much
like a plant. Though with this
difference a plant's complete whereas a
fetus still is journeying the active
virtue labor. So the fetus may move and
feel like a sea sponge and then it
starts to organize the powers seated. At
this point, son, the power that had come
from the begget's heart unfolds and
spreads that nature may see every limb
perfected.
But how the animal becomes a speaking
being you've not yet seen. This point so
hard it led one wiser than you are to
earn in separating from the possible
intellect the soul since he could see no
organ for the mind. So did he teach?
Open your heart to truth. We now have
reached and know that once the brain's
articulation within the fetus has
attained perfection. Then the first
mover turns toward it with joy on seeing
so much art and nature and breast into
it new spirit. Vicorous which draws all
that is active in the fetus into its
substance and becomes one soul that
lives and feels and has
self-consciousness.
That what I say may leave you less
perplexed. Consider the sun's heat that
when combined with sap with that flows
from vines is then made wine. And when
lakesis lacks more threat than souls
divide from the flesh potentially it
bears with it the human and divine. But
with the human powers mute the rest
intelligence and memory and will are
more acute in action than they were.
With no delay the soul falls of itself
astonishingly on one of two shores.
There it learns early what way it will
journey. There once the soul is
circumscribed by space, the power that
gives for me radiates as and as much as
once it formed life limbs and even as
the saturated air since it reflects the
rays the sun has sent takes rainbow
colors as its ornament. So there where
the soul stopped the nearby air takes on
the form that so impressed on it a shape
that is potentially real body. And then
just as a flame will follow after the
fire whenever fire moves. So that new
form becomes the spirit's follower.
Since from that airy body it takes on
its semblance. That soul is called
shade. That shape forms organs for each
sense even for sight. This airy body
lets us speak and laugh. With it we form
the tears inside the size that you
perhaps have heard around this mountain.
Just as we are held fast by longings and
by other sentiments, our shade takes
form. This is the cause of your
astonishment.
>> Okay. So let me explain what he is
saying here. Okay. Okay. And this goes
back to the idea of the morphic fields
that we discussed earlier. Okay. So what
he's saying is this. We know how
the fetus turns into a baby which turns
into a body. Right? That makes sense.
Okay. Um so the baby is in the womb and
at some point the uh fetus becomes a
baby. Okay.
That is his biology. The problem is
consciousness. How does consciousness
happen? And so what um he's saying is
this at a certain point the baby is so
developed. Okay, the baby is so
developed that God can now smile upon
it. And when go when God smiles upon it,
what happens is that these um universal
unconscious that we've discussed, what
it does is that it creates a soul
inside
the baby. Okay, does that make sense? As
the baby develops limbs and
um the full shape of the body, the soul
itself starts to take shape as well.
Okay. And we think that the soul, oh,
it's a spark in us or it's part of the
brain. No, it's actually the body
itself.
Okay. And these are what called morphic
fields.
Morphic fields.
So, think as though your body is now
emitting energy fields. Okay? And that's
how uh Franis was able to easily uh
notice when Edward turned around. Okay?
Does that make sense? because there are
fields around you that feel the world
spiritually around you and um connect
you to the universal consciousness.
Okay. So what happens is that okay the
these fields are now uh resembling your
body. Okay. So each part of your body
has its own field. Your organs have
their own fields. Even when your body
decomposes, these fields are still
around that mimic your old body. And as
such, you can still feel the way that
your old body used to feel. Not as much,
but but there's still some elements to
it. That's how people are able to feel
pain both in hell and in purgatory.
It doesn't make sense, guys.
All right.
Uh yes.
>> What about the souls in heaven? Do they
also have like this?
>> Excuse me.
>> Um what about the souls in heaven?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so this is what we what
we learned in paradise, right? What
happens in heaven is like once you
ascend to the divine light, all these
fields have returned home. So what they
they do so what they do is they bend
they bend to fit heaven. Now does it
make sense? Before these fields bended
to fit your body once you go home to
heaven because of divine light they now
bend to fit the divine light. And so you
lose
basically uh the uh the body form
completely. Okay. As a shade you have
like half half but once you return to
heaven then you become part of the uh
divine unity again.
All right. So that's what he's saying
here. Any questions about this? Yes.
>> Then so is it the soul or the body that
feels hunger
>> when you're starving?
>> Is it?
>> Oh, excuse me.
>> Is it the soul or the body that feels
hunger?
Because well, normally you would say
it's the body needs food. So it like
says to the brain, I need food. But in
your in that perception be different.
>> Okay. So on earth when we starve it's a
physical reaction right it's a physical
reaction does it make sense if if your
body doesn't get enough food the organs
break down and um you die okay but in
purgatory it's a different process so
the idea is that
these this is the gluttony okay this is
the terrace of gluttony and there's a
tree calling to them and saying you know
like you can smell me you can desire me
but you must resist me.
Does that make sense? Okay. So, what's
happening is no longer at a body level
but a soul level. And so, the soul to um
demonstrate its longing yet its
restraint, it becomes much more u
emaciated.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So it's a metaphorical fruit that but so
it's it's not real hunger then because
you
>> okay well they say it would it be real
hunger right because because only if
it's real does it have any meaning if
you have to feel real pain real desire
for it to have any meaning right okay so
but but you need to understand like
imagine two two dimensions okay your
body's ex existing on one dimension your
soul is existing on on another
dimension. And here on earth, the both
are combined together. But in purgatory,
the body loses its um physical form. You
no longer have a body, but the soul
still maintains the semblance of the
body. So you still hunger and you can
still starve, but in a spiritual way.
Does it make sense? So what's happening
here is not at a physical level, but at
a spiritual level.
Did they have food in the other circles
and the other um what Don is saying
here? There's no food. There's no need
for food. Yes. Yes.
>> Yeah. It makes me think about like
David's Psalms that my soul longs for
the Lord as um the the deer longs for
the stream or something and talking
about drinking of this like eternal
water or whatever like his soul. So I
guess it's kind of the same thing like
your soul can thirst for things and so
this these ghosts uh or shadows are yeah
longing for the same and I think there's
also scientific experiment where like
people who lose a limb like your body
thinks that it can still control that
limb and then it can that's how the
robotics can work right so all the
neurons near that aspect makes your uh
brain still controls it so it's kind of
like your soul as long as it thinks that
it still has that body part you can
somehow have that move it like to to be
able to control or feel it.
>> Yeah. It's called phantom limbs. Okay.
>> Phantom limbs. Okay. Where like you lose
actually
um your entire arm, but you still at
some level think it's still there. It's
really strange. Okay. But but but you
can Google phantom limbs. It's it's a
very common um psychological
uh thing. Okay. But but the idea is
this. Okay. The idea is that our souls,
okay, our souls, they only long for one
thing, which is the the divine light,
okay, to be closer to God, right? That's
the divine light. That's what our souls
aspire to. The divine light. But
the problem is that we're inside bodies,
okay? And our bodies has senses which is
say like we have these different desires
like for food,
sex,
water.
Okay. And so we can we become really
confused. We don't know what brings us
happiness. Is it lots of sex? Is it a
Mercedes? Is it um wine? Right? We just
we just become really really confused.
And so that's why we do stupid things.
But once we shed our bodies, then the
souls only desire the divine light.
Okay? Doesn't make sense. The problem
with gluttony is
the memory
of these things, our desire for these
things are still there and we want to
pay penance for this. So our souls
our souls engage in a process of uh
emitiation
which is a denial of the divine light in
order to compensate for our gluttony on
earth. So it's a conscious choice on our
part to starve ourselves in order to pay
penance for um our gluttony on earth.
And how this system works is the tree
um helps us remember
our bodies through sense, right? It
gives it gives us the like the scent of
food and we desire it, but we're but
we're souls. We can't actually eat food
and so we have this emitiation going on.
Does it make sense you guys?
Okay.
And Okay. All right. Let's uh keep on
going.
109. By now we've reached the final
turning, we would meet and took took the
pathway right at which we were
preoccupied with other cares. There from
the wall the mountain hurls its flames,
but from the terrace side there whirls a
wind that pushes back the fire and
limits it. Thus on the open side,
proceeding one by one, we went. I feared
the fire on the left and on the right
the precipice. My guide said, "On this
terrace, it is best to curve your eyes
the least distraction left and right.
Left or right can mean a step you will
regret." Then from the heart of that
great confflration, I heard Sume Dave's
Clemensier sung and was not less keen to
turn my eyes. And I saw spirits walking
in the flames, so that I looked at them
and at my steps sharing the time and had
to look at each. After they'd reached
that hymn's end, virum nonosuo were the
words they cried aloud. Then they began
the hymn in a low voice again. And done
again they cried. Diana kept the woods
and banished Heliche after he she'd felt
the force of Venus's poison. Then they
returned to singing and they praised
aloud those wives and husbands who were
chased as virtue and as matrimony
mandate. This is I think the way these
spirits act as long as they are burned
by fire. This is the cure and this the
nourishment with which one has to heal
the final wound of all.
>> Okay. All right. So, uh we'll go over by
like five minutes. It's fine. Okay. Um
one last question is they are now in the
final terrace which is the um terrorist
of lust.
Why would fire like stepping through
fire help cure you of lust?
>> Uh yes.
Um cuz if you're a lustful person,
you're kind of like consumed by this
like burning desire that you have for
like other people's body. And then so if
you want to pur purify yourself, you
need to be burned um you need to be you
need to be able to like withstand the
burning fire to withstand your burning
desire for like lust.
>> Okay, that makes sense for hell, right?
uh to be punished for your lust through
fire.
But in purgatory, we want to prepare
ourselves for heaven. We want to do
penance and prepare ourselves for
heaven.
>> Is it like cuz some of the times you're
also like purified if you're like burned
into like a very high temperature like
kind of like pottery and stuff. And I
hear in purgatory you are purified
through fire. evident and how you're
just punished by being burned.
>> Okay. Let Yes.
>> Uh I think um lust is not wrong but the
people here they are kind of abusing the
the the pleasure or like the power of
lust so that they need to be they need
to uh correct their um passive.
>> Okay. All right. So so let's continue
the ceramics metaphor. Okay. Why do you
have to put your ceramics into fire?
to harden
>> to harden it. Right. In hell infernal,
how are the lustful being punished?
Yeah. Because they are, you know,
they're being whooped around, right?
Because they are not consistent. Because
they are not hard enough. Do you
understand? They're not firm. Do you
understand? So the fire, the entire
point of fire is to make you firm.
firming your faith, firming your
commitment, firming your devotion. Okay.
That's what the fire is doing, purifying
you, but also basically hardening you.
Okay. All right. So, um that's it.
That's great. That's it for today. Any
questions? Uh tomorrow? Yes. One one
last question, Fred.
>> Just one quick question. Um, there was a
line that really confused me earlier
this morning, which is, "You feel
delight as nature fashioned you to
feel." Is this Dante saying that some
people are more ready to experience the
love of God while they're alive than
others?
>> No. No. That's that's that's what it's
saying. Okay. In Dante, nature and God
are not the same thing. Nature and God
are not the same thing. It's really
important for us to remember this
because in Shakespeare, they're the same
thing. We talked about this yesterday,
right? where professor B was saying well
nature naturalistic I'm like yeah but is
there a god he's like well naturalistic
right so in our world in Shakespeare
world nature is god but in donn's world
it's different because nature gives us
our bodies but god gives us our soul you
understand so the soul aspires to divine
light but the but the body aspires to
material pleasures
okay does that make sense okay all right
thanks guys so tomorrow's the last class
and so um yeah so uh uh think of how
this course has changed you okay and
think about how the divine calling has
impacted you and I love the idea that
you guys having more dreams okay this
this will be really important for
tomorrow's discussion all right I'll see
you everyone Uh-huh.